<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Samaritanism, or, A treatise of comprehending, compounding and tolerating several religions in one church demonstrating the equity, and necessity of the act and late vote of Parliament against non-conformists, from reason, the ancient church, and the opinions and practice of papists and Puritans now plotting and pleading for toleration.</title>
            <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36671</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15869132</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15869132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104650</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104650)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1154:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Samaritanism, or, A treatise of comprehending, compounding and tolerating several religions in one church demonstrating the equity, and necessity of the act and late vote of Parliament against non-conformists, from reason, the ancient church, and the opinions and practice of papists and Puritans now plotting and pleading for toleration.</title>
                  <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel and are to be sold by Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1664?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Perrinchief.</note>
                  <note>T.p. is cropped, with imprint date lacking. Publication date suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104650:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SAMARITANISM</hi> OR, A TREATISE OF <hi>Comprehending, Compounding,</hi> and <hi>Tolerating</hi> SEVERAL RELIGIONS IN ONE CHURCH, DEMONSTRATING, The Equity and Neceſſity of the Act, and Late Vote of Parliament againſt <hi>Non-conformiſts.</hi> From Reaſon, the Ancient Church, and the Opinions, and Practice of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Puritans,</hi> now Plotting, and Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Broom,</hi> in Little <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104650:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104650:2"/>
            <head>Of Liberty of RELIGION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP I. <hi>A Preparative Enquiry into the Nature of Human Eccleſiaſtical Societies, in general.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAN being a Sociable Creature, according to the Obſervation of the Philoſopher, and Common Experience; That Human Societies ought to excell Herds and flocks of Cattel, is moſt reaſonable to conclude. For, a Multitude is one thing, and a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety another; and differ as much as a <hi>Common,</hi> and a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> Yet, as ſuch is the ſagacity and ſubtilty of ſome Animals as that witty Philoſophers have had enough to do to diſtinguiſh the ſupream acts of ſome Beaſts from the reaſonable actions of Men; ſo have ſome acute Obſervers of the nature and order of certain Animals in community, diſcovered ſo much <hi>Decorum</hi> and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they have entitled meerly ſenſitive Creatures to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Human Societies: and do eſpy a ſemblance of Monarchy in the Regiment of Bees, and Popular Government in that of Ants. But the definition which <hi>Bodin</hi> gives of a Commonwealth,
<note place="margin">Bodinus de Rep. lib. 1. init. <hi>Reſpubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca est Familiarum rerum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> interipſas communium ſumma potestate ac ratione moderate multitudo.</hi>
                  </note> doth ſufficiently put a difference between them, which is this.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104650:3"/>A Commonwealth is a multitude of Families and Common Matter adminiſtred by a Supream Power and Reaſon: For what ever we may judge, there is in ſome brutiſh Communities a Supream Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; and that is founded on Senſe and natural Inſtinct: And in Human Societies there is, and of neceſſity muſt be, a Supream Authority founded on Reaſon and Natural Inſtinct. For as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe proceedeth from Natural Inſtinct given to Beaſts; ſo Reaſon proceedeth from, or is the Natural Inſtinct in Man: The Supream act in Man being termed Reaſon; and the higheſt in Beaſts, Senſe. Though I confeſs the matter remains very difficult ſtill, to diſtinguiſh clearly the one from the other; not in a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition (for that is eaſie enough to frame) but in the exerciſe of Acts, whether they belong to, or may be comprehended in the definition of Reaſon or no? Let others ſtrain their Wits to that purpoſe; our preſent Subject calls us another way. And in the firſt place to note freely the prety, pitiful, and fine preſumptions of divers enquirers into the grounds and occaſions of Human So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties; which becauſe, forſooth, taken from Reaſon at firſt, ſome Men have imagined that Natural Inſtinct in Man was not princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal in the Conſtitution of Commonwealths. Some therefore have wittily (at leaſt as they ſuppoſe) ſaid, That neceſſity was the cauſe why men combined together in one: Neceſſity of heat drove divers ſtragling Men to the ſame fire; and meeting there, they took up ſeveral Diſcourſes and Counſels for their common Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. Others more ſeriouſly, if not more wiſely, are of opinion. That ſelf-defence and preſervation againſt common Adverſaries impelled many perſons to aſſociate together, and to elect ſome principal Defender of their Perſons, and Directer of their Affairs. But they conſider not, nor give any account how ſuch Enemies to ſome, came firſt to conſpire into ſuch a powerful Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, as to be able to offend others. Was this occaſioned likewiſe from fear of others? If ſo, I will demand perpetually, How came thoſe others ſo together? And at length it muſt of neceſſity be anſwered, From ſome other cauſe, &amp; that cauſe muſt be at length, Natural Reaſon, Juſtice, and Law; whereby, according to Man, ſome were obliged to Subjection, as ſome had right of Dominion. Now what manner of Dominion that was, I leave to be inquired into.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104650:3"/>
               <p>Yet withal I cannot but ſmile a little at the boldneſs and vain preſumption of ſuch who paſſing over the moſt viſible original of Government, and what <hi>de facto</hi> it firſt was, (which certainly in all reaſon muſt needs be the moſt natural way of making out the truth) do betake themſelves to the uncertain mazes and labyrinths of human imagination, which we find to be ſwayed and bribed to argue and conclude according to Self-intereſt, and particular caſes of their own. Thus we read the Aſſertors of the <hi>German</hi> Empire to ſtrain their Reaſons to prove the Conſtitution of that Government according to the famous Golden Bull of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, Emperor, to be moſt perfect, and natural. But Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſheweth us plainly, that nothing hath divided, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently weaken'd, more that once moſt potent and flouriſhing Nation, than thoſe Immunities and Laws have; and render'd the Supream Power ſo uncertain and obſcure, that 'tis an hard matter to find where it is ſeated; or, if ſo to find that to be a Monarchy, and not a Commonwealth, or at leſt a Combination of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies and Commonwealths.</p>
               <p>The like courſe hath <hi>Contarenus</hi> taken in his deſcription of the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> (for that too muſt be held to be moſt natural) bending his Wits to draw the Law and courſe of Nature to a conformity to his reaſon, and his reaſon to the condition of that Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>The ſame courſe hath <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (and other, eſpecially Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Authors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) followed in his Previous Controverſies to his Diſputations of the Power, and Regiment of the Pope, contending hard, that the Government is moſt Reaſonable and Chriſtian, which ſuits beſt with the Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop and Clergy. And ſome have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to that degree of admiration of that Form, that they have ventured to affirm, That Chriſt had not done wiſely, if he had not ordained and diſpoſed matters juſt as they now ſtand among them. And are not there to be found amongſt us, who have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the very ſame expreſſions in behalf of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery?</p>
               <p>And this eying of inſtances rather than following the clue of his own moſt rational Wit was that which cauſed the Philoſopher <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to be ſo inconſtant to himſelf in his Politicks. For
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104650:4"/>when he handled the caſe abſtractly, he judged excellently of the true nature of Government, and the moſt natural Government. But then, having before his eyes what great offence he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily give to his Country of <hi>Greece,</hi> which abounded with ſeveral Polities of a ſtrange nature; he found it requiſite to ſtrain his Leather to their Laſts. Eſpecially conſidering, that if thoſe Nations, who were for Wit and Learning, the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of all the World, ſhould diſreliſh his Schemes (as in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability they would, as they diſagreed from their plat-forms) it might prove an incurable prejudice to his Works. For, as it is ſeen in Religion, it happens in Civil Polities too, that the more it is with acuteneſs and ſubtilty penetrated, and diſcuſſed, the more corrupt and degenerate it is in the uſe and practice.</p>
               <p>For that there is a Government of Divine appointment, as well in Secular as Religious Societies, is not to be much doubted of; and that all <hi>in ſpecie</hi> cannot be ſuch, is evident from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and contrariety of them: For the voice of God is either that innate direction, and natural, and indeliberate election and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to which Men by a tacite univerſal conſent do tend, and plainly is to one kind of Political Government only, and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to any, as by inſtances may be given from all people, whoſe firſt Governors were always Monarchs without exception. For that after a State hath for a long time been founded and ſelted, Men out of ſeveral regards and motives ſet their Wits on work, and changed the ſame, not to that Form which really was beſt but beſt pleaſed them, cannot prejudice the title it hath to be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Natural: for as much as we ſee that nothing is ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or indiſputably divine, but it may be, and hath been altered, and thwarted by the bold and unquiet Wits of Men; and no where are ſuch alterations oftner to be found than where Wit and Learning moſt flouriſh; for from an opinion theſe breed in men, are they tempted to deſpiſe the ſimplicity, and direct path of Natural reaſon to ſeek more fine and curious ways of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the common Intereſt; Or, the voice of God is that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural word of God which gives neither precedent nor rule, nor precept for above one Government in either of the Polities.</p>
               <p>Some ſuppoſe to moderate and compound the matter by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that Government in general is of Divine Inſtitution but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104650:4"/>God hath left it to the liberty of Men to make choice of one Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or kind of Government, according as it ſhall ſute beſt with the Genius and Humours of the people to be governed. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this I have more to object than may be proper for this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. I ſhall therefore demand firſt, By what Rules of Reaſon, or Philoſophy ſuch Men proceed? for, hitherto in other things it was never heard of that God ſhould poſitively create or ordain a thing in the Genus or Species, and ſo that the <hi>Individuum</hi> under them ſhould take its being and ſubſiſt; when as, what ever Being is in the Genus or Kind is owing to the Particular ſubſiſting by it ſelf. For more plainneſs: Can we ſay, that God firſt made a living Creature in general, and from thence ſprang Man and Beaſt? or an Horſe, and <hi>Socrates?</hi> Did he not rather firſt of all create this Man in particular, and ſo Human Nature had its original ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; and firſt create this Individual Beaſt, and ſo from thence that nature of Animals take its denomination and being. And thus was it in the Inſtitution of Governments. God cannot rationally nor truly be ſaid to make Government in general, or ordain it, and not firſt inſtitute ſome one particular Government, from whence the like might be termed Divine, and the Species it ſelf ſuch.</p>
               <p>Conſider we farther, how more than ridiculous it were that Divine Inſtitution ſhould be of ſuch immenſe extent and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as that it were impoſſible for the boldeſt and wildeſt wit of Man to invent ſuch a form as ſhould not be divine? Which muſt of neceſſity follow, or the quite contrary, that no Government is of divine appointment <hi>in ſpecie;</hi> both which are equally and utterly falſe and abſurd. The former, in that it makes Divine Right like the fabulous fiction of Poets concerning Victory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Armies engaging, hanging in the Air, and hovering over mens heads, until the main ſtroke be ſtruck, and Men have voted eſpecially for one ſort of Government, and then forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with down comes Divine Right amain, and lighting on it makes it undoubtedly Divine. And to hold that no Government is of Divine Original, is to deſtroy all Right of Rule; and, as ſome enemies to Mankind have with impudence and ſtupidity (even while they ſeek nothing ſo much as to appear tranſcendent) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to reduce all kinds and actual poſſeſſion of Empire to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104650:5"/>the baſe principle of Beaſts, ſtrength and force; and his it is, as well in Juſtice as Act, who can catch it. Such a Philoſopher indeed as this (and, as Reaſon and Religion now goes, ſuch an one is no ſmall fool amongſt us) deſerves to have the edge of his acute wit turned againſt him, and to be diſputed with, as Men are wont to do with his fellow beaſts deſtructive to Mankind, with a Kennel of hounds, ſpears, and ſtaffs.</p>
               <p>But I return to demand further, Whether that Charter is extant, to whom it properly and by divine intention pertains, that Men may choſe what Government they pleaſe? That which God would have is ſufficiently made known unto us from the nature and form of that which by his ſpecial Providence firſt, and only appeared for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years in the World. Thoſe which ſucceeded and excluded the Primitive, were the effect of paſſions principally: But no ſooner had Luſt, Intereſt, and Error cauſed men to introduce their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, but inſtantly Nature and Scripture were drawn to aſſert and ſuſtain them; as Baſtards left in diſtreſs and helpleſs, are put to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Women to Nurſe and bring up.</p>
               <p>I know very well, and readily grant that all ſorts of Governments have ſomewhat Divine in them; but this they have not as ſeveral ſorts, nor as ſuch Forms, but in reſpect of the matter they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in, which principally is that truly Divine Law, Juſtice; which as to the matter of it, may as really, though not ſo regularly, be adminiſtred in one kind, as another.</p>
               <p>But he that would faithfully and ſucceſſively ſettle his judgment in the true and genuine kind of Government, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, ought not to proceed in that long, tedious, and moſt uncertain way of Mens minds and Intereſts, of enquiring, which of all ſeems moſt reaſonable, moſt equal, moſt holy, and beneficial to the ends of all Rule; and conclude that to be ſo, which ſeems to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to be bleſſed moſt plentifully with theſe; but muſt impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and ſincerely enquire after the <hi>Fact</hi> immediately; which of all theſe have the faireſt and cleareſt proofs of being <hi>de facto</hi> inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted of God. For, a quite contrary method may be obſerved in the Will and Laws of Men, and of God: Man choſeth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees a thing becauſe it is good and laudable; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, becauſe God wills and ordains a thing, therefore is it good of neceſſity; according as <hi>Gerſon</hi> hath excellently obſerved,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104650:5"/>
                  <hi>Deus non ideò vult res ed extra fieri quia bonae ſunt,
<note place="margin">Gerſon de Conſolatione Theologiae. Proſ. 2.</note> quemadmodum movetur humana voluntas ex objectione boni, vel veri vel apparentis. Eſt è contra potius, quod ideò res ad extra bonae ſunt, quia Deus vult eas tales eſſe: Ideóque ſi vellet eas vel non eſſe, vel aliter eſſe, id quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que jam bonum eſſet, &amp;c.</hi> Thus he. For inſtance, We all, or moſtly agree, that the Parts of Man's body are placed moſt aptly for uſe and ſervice of the whole, and moſt beautifully for ornament placed in the ſame. Yet ſuppoſing that it had been the will of God to have ſet the Noſe of Man behind him, his Eyes in his Breſt, his Ears on the Crown of his Head, and his Mouth on the Navel of his Belly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute this had been the moſt wiſe, beautiful, and uſeful order. In like manner, had it ſeemed good to God to caſt Civil and Church-Government into any other ſhape, form, or condition than actually he hath, it were not to be queſtion'd but it would be moſt perfect and excellent. From all which (ending this Chapter) I infer theſe Concluſions as certain and pious:</p>
               <p>Firſt, That both Polities have a Government eſpecially Divine.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I conclude, That Government ſo Divine is not to be altered under ſpecious pretexts, and Human ratiocinations and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions offering themſelves, that another ſort would ſerve the ends of Community better: For the fault may be, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is, in the knottineſs and croſs-grainneſs of the piece of Wood, and not in the Tool, or Artificer. And more reaſonable it is divers times, the People ſhould be changed, than their Laws or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; though the contrary is commonly ſeen, that when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in untractableneſs, they caſt off the accuſation from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by chaſtiſing the Laws, controverting Titles, and quarel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the imperfections and inconveniences of that Government they live under, as not good enough for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104650:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>A Second General Preparation to the determining the Queſtion, by removing vulgar miſtakes concerning Tyranny, Antichriſtianiſm, Chriſtian Liberty, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, and Moderation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is too plainly ſeen, that words, which at firſt were inſtituted to ſerve Man's underſtanding, and guide it into the knowledg of things, do command, pervert, and hurry it into many miſtakes and errors: Or perhaps, to ſpeak more properly, the vulgar uſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them cauſeth this miſchief. And hence it is that an opprobrious name maliciouſly or ignorantly given, and commonly applied is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſufficient to captivate ordinary Minds into an evil opinion of things undeſervedly. Call therefore a Government Tyrannical, Antichriſtian, Extream, Immoderate, and againſt Chriſtian Liberty; this with the Common ſort, proves ſuch a Government ought not to be endured, though it be not all proved that ſuch terms properly belong to it, nor indeed ſuch perſons who are ſo liberal of their ill language know well what they ſay, or whereof they affirm. Let us endeavour then to come very briefly to a true notion of ſome of them.</p>
               <p>Concerning Tyranny then, a grand and current miſtake there is that it is properly a <hi>Species</hi> or kind of Government; which is true indeed if it be taken in the Ancienteſt, not Modern ſenſe, for the ſame with Monarchy, or the Government of One. And thus in truth divers have of late taken it, ſuppoſing that Monarchy and Tyranny are the ſame; and that the Rule of One abſolutely muſt of neceſſity be Tyranny, which is altogether as true as the other extreme they fall into, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Government by many is a Government of Liberty. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> when he ſaid, That Monarchy eaſily degenerates into Tyranny, did not ſay or mean that it was ſo in its own nature: Neither, did he ſay <hi>Polycratie</hi> did not, nor could fall into the ſame. For he that will be at the ſmall pains to weigh the matter ſincerely, ſhall eaſily perceive that Tyranny is no Government of it ſelf, but the corruption of Government. And Liberty is no more eſſential to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104650:6"/>
                  <hi>Ariſtocracie,</hi> or ſuch like Government, Conſtituted of many Rulers, than to <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and that dreadful thing, called Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, is altogether as incident to the Rule of Many; as when One alone has the Supream Power: Nay, there muſt of neceſſity be an Arbitrary Power, and Actually is, in all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths,
<note place="margin">Anarchie of mixed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</note> as hath been Irrefragably Demonſtrated by others alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who are not of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who are often Cenſured, for driving matters of this nature too high. For it is impoſſible any Commonwealth ſhould ſubſiſt, or continue without a Supream Abſolute Power; and where ever this is, there is that we call Arbitrary Power. Many People indeed, obſerving the evils of this, have ſo Framed their Government, and Conſtituted Governours as to prevent the ſame; and have allmoſt infinitely multiplyed Governors, and Inſpectors over Governors, and Check over Check, but could never find ſucceſs anſwerable; the laſt Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of all therefore againſt Courts, Princes, and Greateſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills, have been to entitle the People in Groſs, to take account of ſuch Irregularities: but ſuch a remedy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Populum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem coetum multitadinis, ſed coetum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris conſenſu &amp; utilitatis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atum eſſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat.</hi> Scipio. Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronianus <hi>apud</hi> Auguſtinum <hi>de Civitate Dei.</hi> Lib. 2. cap. 21.</note> as it could never ſo much as take place, for as much as never did, or can the People concurr Univerſally to ſuch Ends but the <hi>Major,</hi> or more Active, and buſie part carried the name of all, which commonly is a piece of as great injuſtice, and injury, as any they would cure by ſuch jealous Vigilancy: and if it could be done, Were not this as Arbitrary a Proceeding, as the very Firſt of all?</p>
               <p>There is therefore, and muſt be in all Government an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and Arbitrary Power. Now, that, when this Supremeſt Power is veſted in One, it muſt preſently be called a Tyrannie; when in many, Liberty, is a miſerable cheat of the Common-people by ambitious, and diſcontented perſons, ſeeking the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves, by the Oppreſſion of others. For, as the Apoſtle in another Caſe hath it; <hi>Thou art inexcuſable, O man, who ſo ever thou art that judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt, doſt the ſame things.</hi> So that if it be unjuſt for One who is Supream, to do ſuch a thing towards ſuch as are Subject to him, it is unjuſt for Many ſo to do; and if it be Tyrannical for Him, it is Tyrannical in Many, even in a <hi>Senate:</hi> For, what is Tyrannie, but an exceſſive uſe, or exerciſe of Power, contrary to the Law of Reaſon, and Juſtice:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104650:7"/>So that Tyrannie, doth not conſiſt in the abundance of Power, but in the abuſe: as other Moral Vices, do not conſiſt in full power to offend, but in the ill uſe of ſuch Power. For, as Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs conſiſteth not in having plenty of Wine, nor Gluttonie in having choice and command of rich and various Fare (and ſo in other things); but in taking too liberally, and inordinately of them: So Tyrannie is not the uncontrollableneſs of Power in One Perſon or more, but the unreaſonable and immoderate uſe according to Power. For he indeed is a Tyrant that thus carries himſelf, and that Council is Tyrannical, yea, that People is Tyrannical, which contrary to the Law of Reaſon Invadeth, and Mutilateth the Rights of Dominion belonging to their Governours, which may be their Property as juſtly, and reaſonably, as any Goods, or Poſſeſſions belonging to Subjects, may be ſo termed, in reſpect of them. A thing, which if it were imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and conſcionably conſidered, me-thinks People would be more modeſt, than to think all thoſe Privileges, and Liberties (they can, by flattery, craft, or taking advantage of neceſſities into which their Governours may be brought, gain to themſelves) lawful ſpoil; or indeed, though at firſt ſight they may appear ſo, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for themſelves: For ſuppoſe we, that a people ſtudious of Liberty, ſhould not only procure a Law that they ſhould be free from all contributions to common good but what voluntarily they ſhould pleaſe to give;
<note place="margin">
                     <p>Auguſt. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei.</hi> Lib. 2. ca. 21.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Plutarch. De ſera Numinis. &amp;</hi> Pſal. 94.20.</p>
                  </note> but likewiſe, by ſuch a Law, that they ſhould never be compelled (which we vulgarly, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly call, Preſſed) to the Warrs; this ſurely would ſeem a glorious Liberty, and benefit to the common ſort, but really would in ſhort time prove the ruine of the whole. There is ſuch an Immunity claimed by the Commons of the Confederate <hi>Netherlands,</hi> which hath endangered; and certainly, had not the Governours found out ſome prettie tricks to elude it, had una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably brought thoſe Commonwealths to nothing. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Book of the City of God, tells us, That <hi>Scipio</hi> in <hi>Tullie</hi> calls an unjuſt King a Tyrant; and unjuſt Nobles, Governing, a Faction; and ſpeaking of the exceſs of Popular Government, to that, ſaith he, <hi>Nomen non reperit, niſi ut etiam &amp; ipſum Tyrannum vocaret, i.e.</hi> He could find no name for them, but Tyrants alſo: Neither have ſuch juſt excuſe, becauſe perhaps they have a Law on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104650:7"/>their ſide. For the Law it ſelf, may have been extorted; and, if freely Enacted, yet unjuſt in it ſelf, as that we laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; and that <hi>Law</hi> of which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>framing miſchief;</hi> and that Law, which many vehemently plead for in Church-Diſcipline, as that wherein conſiſteth (as they fondly, and falſly imagine, or perhaps would ſeem to believe rather) Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty, That every man ſhould do as he pleaſes, in things ſo Indifferent that they are not under any Precept or Prohibition of Gods Word: For this would inevitably produce differences; and differences, in ſuch inconſiderable matters, will infallibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Animoſities and Diviſions in greater matters, and there terminate in the overthrow of all Diſcipline, or Government: I ſay, All Diſcipline. Now there is a Diſcipline which Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> held to be a third Eſſential part of a true Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cartwright</hi> in Second Reply <hi>p.</hi> 53.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Id.</hi> Firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. <hi>pa.</hi> 14.</p>
                  </note> if we believe Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> relating his opinion or his own: Which is, That matters of Diſcipline, and kind of Government, are not to be diſtinguiſhed from matters neceſſary to Salvation and Faith: So that however they ſeem to be of this deſtructive Opinion (and indeed, they often and plainly affirm ſo much) yet they be no longer of it, than till ſuch time as the Power be in their own hands: juſt as the Miller ſtops the courſe of the Waters, not that he is abſolutely againſt Rivers, what ever he may ſeem to be, but till he ſhall find it neceſſary for his own Griſt. Now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Application of what we have ſaid, concerning Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which our Church-Government is commonly, and boldly charged with by Sectaries, and particularly, in their Synodical Letters to Tranſmarine Churches; They may learn at Length, that no Government in its Nature is Tyrannical, but the evil Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of any Government makes any ſo, though Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical. For it is not neceſſary, that the <hi>Perſian, Turkiſh,</hi> or <hi>Tararian</hi> Government ſhould be Tyrannical, more than That of <hi>Venice,</hi> or of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi> For theſe have as Abſolute and Arbitrary Dominion as they. 'Tis true, theſe have more Moderate and Favourable Laws of Ruling than They: But who ſhall conſtrain them to obſerve them, if they pleaſe to break them? The People? So may the People bring thoſe Barbarous Kings to more equal dealing, if they can, as well as the other. If therefore Many in Authority, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104650:8"/>do the ſame things, and have as much Power as One; the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of this differs from the Tyranny of them, juſt as much as a pound of Lead doth from a pound of Feathers; which is no ſmall matter with vulgar Judges. Therefore, until Reformers of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments deny the power to themſelves which they deny to others, and the exerciſe thereof; let them accuſtom their mouths to more ingenuous and ſincere language, and either forbear to traduce others with that ignominious term, or begin to hallow it by their profeſſion and practice.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Aristot. Ethic. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Baſil. M.</hi> in <hi>Princip. Prov. Iſido. Peluſiot. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epi.</hi> 194. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epist.</hi> 142.</note> For 'tis but changing the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar into the plural number, and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s deſcription of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant will ſuit as well with States and Claſſes, as with King and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: <hi>viz. The Tyrants ſeek their own good, but Princes ſeek the good of them they govern:</hi> Wherein he is followed by Saint <hi>Baſil;</hi> as is he, by <hi>I ſidore Peluſiotes.</hi> But let us proceed to what follows.</p>
               <p>Next in order, nature, and abuſe, is infamous Extremity, immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateneſs, or want of moderation, in managing Controverſies, and compoſingand curing Diviſions and Differences: For, whoſo ſhall go under ſuch imputations of the Vulgar ſhall have enough to anſwer for, though no more be objected againſt him. Let us ſee therefore what is Moderation, and conſequently Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, according to vulgar acception. After this manner then, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is the ſame in effect with the art of cleaving of Billets, cutting or chopping a thing in the middle, and dividing the live-Child into two equal parts between the unjuſt pretender, and the true Mother, without any due conſideration of the cauſe it ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch.</hi> in <hi>Sympoſias.</hi>
                  </note> in juſtice, but the peace of different Parties. For as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> obſerveth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>With Fools and Knaves there is no ſuch thing as the Mean, as to the Thing.</hi> But if Men be extreamly diſtant from, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to a thing or perſon, then preſently do they accuſe the ſame of Extreams, not conſidering that it is in the power of any Man to declare &amp; denominate a thing extream, by his only act of extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departing from it, as eaſily as it is in his power by turning himſelf about, to cauſe a thing to ſtand to the left or right hand.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104650:8"/>If then to reconcile Matters and come to a Mediocrity, we ſhall think it fit to clap into the middle, and give one of the Diſſenters one part, and another, the other; we ſhall quickly diſpatch and deſtroy all Vertue, all Religion, and all Juſtice, in pretending fairly, and intending foully to conſerve them. But Truth, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> hath wiſely noted,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. de Adulatore.</note> is to be ſought out <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i.e.</hi> for Vertue's ſake, not for the extream vice: Unleſs therefore Men ſhall firſt agree upon a rule and ſtandard to meaſure opinions and actions, and accuſations, beſides what is famed or defamed for Extream, it is in vain and fooliſh to talk of Moderation or extream. For, had our Anceſtors held only to that kind of trial, and accommodating differences either in State or Church; we had had neither Juſtice, nor Religion, to ſtrive or contend about at preſent; or, at leaſt, that far from the true. For firſt, <hi>Judaiſm</hi> may be ſaid to be a Mean between <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianiſm; Popery</hi> a Mean between <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſm:</hi> Again, the <hi>Reformation</hi> a Mean between <hi>Papiſm</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſm;</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Reformation,</hi> a Mean between <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm:</hi> And, if we muſt be forced to farther Moderation ſtill, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency</hi> will be found a Mean between <hi>Presbyteriſm</hi> and <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> Government, as <hi>Presbyteriſm</hi> is a Mean between <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Independency;</hi> and <hi>Independency</hi> a Mean between <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> a Mean between <hi>Independency</hi> and <hi>Quakeriſm;</hi> and ſo on, till the wit of Man ſhall be able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent no more Extreams; which whether that will ever be, I know not. Now would I demand, (if it were lawful) Which of all theſe is truly eligible for the Mean ſake? and when that ſhall be pitched on and choſen, Upon what account and ground? Muſt it not be rather becauſe of ſome ſpecial Vertue proper to it as coming neerer to that we conſtitute and propound to our ſelves, as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rule and Principle, than for that it ſtands between two Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, which is common alſo to that Religion which we reject? For 'tis evident by Antiquity, that by the fair face of Mediocrity the <hi>Arians</hi> under <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperor proſpered to the couſenage of the ſimpler, and overthrow of the wiſer Catholicks. But how well <hi>Hilary</hi> thought of this method of Pacification and quieting ſtirs in the Church,
<note place="margin">Hilarius contra Constant.</note> theſe his words to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> plainly teſtifie, <hi>Haec ille pater tuus humanarum mortium docuit, vincere
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104650:9"/>ſine contumacia, jugulare ſine gladio, perſequi ſine infamia, odir ſine ſuſpicione, mentiri ſine intelligentia, profiteri fine fide, blandiri ſine bonitate, agere quod velis, nec manifeſtare quae velis, i. e.</hi> This your Father, the mortal Enemy to man taught you, to Conquer without Fierceneſs, to Stab without a Sword, to make Profeſſion and yet have no Faith, to flatter without goodneſs, to obtain your will, and yet not to diſcover your will. Thus he. And this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and generally do they, who contend for Moderation, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many, and great Inſtances, as may already be given of their condeſcenſions and conceſſions, from whom ſtill boldly and afreſh more Moderation is exacted, as if nothing had been done to ſeek their Peace and good Opinion; whoſe immodeſty and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs will not ſuffer them to reſt, ſo long as they have any hope left them to obtain their Ends, under the ſpecious pretext of Moderation: For if what, and as often as, they demand, be granted; upon that account, they muſt of neceſſity, in time (and that not long) exhauſt and quite deſtroy them inſenſibly: If they be not gratified in this, ſo fair and Popular requeſt; then will they ſhrewdly endanger their Reputation and Intereſt, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them under the Odium and Infamy with the Multitude, for Perſons in Extreams, and who will yield nothing for Peace and Unitie's ſake. But for my own particular, I had rather be Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed than Cheated; and ſuffer the ſame loſs by open violence and aggreſſions, than by fair frauds, by which I muſt believe at the ſame time I am dealt Friendly, and Equally with.</p>
               <p>It being then in the Power of any ſingle Perſon, and much more of a Faction, to make a Church, or, more truly, to denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it, Extream and Immoderate, when ever they pleaſe to run far enough from it, by their roving Inventions and Innovations; When will there be any reſt, or ſtability from ſuch accuſers; if ſuch a Church ſhall preſently be obliged by the Sacred Bonds of Charity, Unity, and Peace, to leave its ground and follow them, at leſt in part, and to relinquiſh its Poſſeſſion and Right, leſt by the foreſaid Engine of ſhew and pretence of Moderation, it be turned out of doors? Surely, God muſt be truſted in ſuch Caſes, if there were no other reaſon (as there are many and weighty) beſides the neceſſity of diſcouraging ſuch Attempts, which would never be wanting, when ſuch ſucceſs is hoped for, upon ſuch general and weak, though plauſible, Pleas.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104650:9"/>
               <p>It is wont to be ſaid, that all this may be true, for it is not fit all Pretenders and Opinions ſhould be Tolerated, or yielded to; but this makes nothing againſt the Sober, Godly, and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Party, who can do ſomewhat, in order to a Reconciliation; and keep cloſe to the Rule of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>I do obſerve, that the beſt Arms (even ſuch men have to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with), are, very frequent and large praiſes of themſelves, and profuſe ſelf-commendation, which hath had wonderful great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: For if you demand an Argument, and ſome competent Proof that they are ſo Conſciencious, or how poſſibly they can be ſaid to be ſo, who have been ſo enormous in Sins of a Party, and not Perſonal Sins; you ſhall find ſhameful tergiverſation, or more ſhameful Juſtification of ſuch Practiſes, as, in our eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation no Sober, Honeſt, or truly Conſciencious man can be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, and much leſs defend.</p>
               <p>And as touching the great Regard, pretended to be had to the Word of God, we ſee no cauſe to take them at their Word, or that they ſhould meaſure, and judge their own Laſt. It is a ſtronger and more reaſonable Proof, that they have not the Scriptures on their ſide, than any they can bring that they have, That all indifferent ſtanders by, give it againſt them: I mean, the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Practiſe of the beſt and ancienteſt Churches</p>
               <p>Neither will the Doctrine of Chriſtian Liberty relieve theſe; if better underſtood, than vulgarly it is. For, not to make a ſet Diſpute of that Subject at preſent, two general Errors may be noted which have evil Influence upon men: Firſt, That Chriſtian Liberty is only Negative, being completed in a freedom from Judaical Servitude, or Bondage under <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law; or not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was indiſpenſably Impoſed by that Law, on that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and not in any thing Poſitive, or a Licence to act more than it was free or Lawful for them. Though I do not find that it was by <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, made utterly Unlawful, for that People to Act any thing, beſides what was Commanded expreſſely by it; It is plain, that in proceſs of time they did contrive many things Extrinſecally related to the Worſhip of God. Neither are ſuch their Ordinances any where reprehended in Scripture; but ſuch are often, which are contrary to their Law, or juſtle out the orders of God, and his precepts, and theſe are the places brought ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104650:10"/>againſt Human Inventions ſubſervient to God's command; very ignorantly, or peeviſhly. But however, Liberty of Chriſtians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth as well to the Affirmative as Negative part; that is, to do thoſe things which are not prohibited any ways by God's Word, as well as not to do thoſe things which the <hi>Jews</hi> were bound to do. Hence it follows, that, were it ſo, that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was tyed up ſo ſtrictly (which I do not believe) that it could not act any thing circumſtantiating the ſervice of God but what was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly required, yet Evangelical Liberty, being as well of a far more ample as noble condition, doth permit ſuch things, contrary to the ſuperſtition of late Paſtors.</p>
               <p>Another Miſtake is concerning the proper ſeat or ſubject of Evangelical Liberty. For, divers there are that ſuppoſe that ſuch Liberty we now treat of (for I know there are divers other ſorts of far more excellent nature, but not concerning us at preſent) belongeth immediately and entirely, to each ſingle good Chriſtian; which is far from truth and ſobriety to conceive: For Chriſt gave this Donative primarily and immediately to his Church and the Adminiſtrators thereof; that they, according to Chriſt's Charter, ſhould have liberty to inſtitute, abrogate, order, and diſpoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſuch Rites and Obſervances as ſhall ſeem to them moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to the Faith and Worſhip of God under the Goſpel; yet with ſuch limitations both for number and nature, that none be introduced contrary to the tenor thereof, or Analogy of Faith, or tend to the burying of any integral part or practiſe thereof under ſuch rubbiſh; yet are not preſently all private Chriſtians allowed to preſide over their Superiors, to the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining what is of evil conſequence, and what not, againſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick judgment: For Inſtance, To have power to determine the eating of Fleſh on Friday or not, is undoubtedly a Liberty E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical; but 'tis not immediately poſited in every particular Chriſtian, but the Church Repreſentative; and private perſons have no liberty but as it is diſpenſed by publick Authority. When I call this a Liberty Evangelical, I mean not as too many do, as if ſuch an indifferency muſt properly belong to Chriſtians; for it doth not: For Infidels and Heathen have that liberty as fully as Chriſt's Church; and they in Authority amongſt them may as well grant or deny this Liberty as Chriſtians; and no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104650:10"/>queſtion but ſuch as are ſubject to them ſhould offend if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly refuſed to comply with their Superiors orders. Does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, think we, Chriſtian Religion and Liberty exempt us from that kind of obedience which is naturally due? For my part, that I hold a double obligation, rather of Chriſtians to ſubmit; and that I can rather pitty, than help ſuch as are of the contrary Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is all that I ſhall ſay at this time: Yet we ſee that too common amongſt us, which <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf end eavoured to ſcoff men out of, in theſe Words,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin.</hi> Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Videas quoſdam quibus ſua libertas non videtur conſiſtere, niſi per eſum carnium die Veneris in ejus poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem venerint, i.e.</hi> You may ſee ſome who ſuppoſe their Liberty cannot hold, unleſs they take Poſſeſſion of it, by eating Fleſh on <hi>Fridays.</hi> To conclude then, It is directly repugnant to Chriſtian Liberty to deny, the Church hath power to appoint the uſe, or diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe of things Indifferent; and 'tis abſolutly inconſiſtent with Evangelical Piety, and the power of Godlineſs (which conſiſt much in denying our own Wills and Appetites) to glory how eaſily we Contemn ſuch Lawful Orders.</p>
               <p>I had thought to have ſaid ſomewhat, againſt the bold Charge of Antichriſtianiſm laid to our Church; and a reaſon, why men that cannot Rule us muſt not obey it: But I perceive the Feavour of our late Reformers to be ſomewhat abated, and like men newly come out of Calentures, they begin to come to their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſee they were monſtrouſly out, though not ſo much to their Reaſon, as to make ſatisfaction for ſuch Phrantick Miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by a ſober retractation, and diſabuſing of Men, (as in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they are bound) from that, and ſuch like Extravagancies.</p>
               <p>But for Peace-ſake, and to prevent a Schiſm, we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to our Brethren, who (to uſe their own Phraſe, which they beſt know what it means) can come up to us in many things. But what means this great and ſuddain Change in theſe men? Are not they the very ſame, who formerly made it Criminal, yea Capital to Preach Peace, and propound Reconciliation? Yes ſure, but Times, not Manners are altered. Surely ſomewhat extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary is at the bottom of all this. They Act not according to Nature, but outward neceſſity: and ſuch a Peace is not worth the having, which can never be held any longer, than men ſhall be able to break it, or work their ends by Inſinuations and fair
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104650:11"/>Promiſes; open force failing them. Like as it is ſeen with an impure Aſſailant of Virginity, the party being Reſcued by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Providence out of his wicked Hands, he turns to her again, and tempts her to his Luſt by promiſes of Marriage; but having obtained his ends, deſpiſes, whom he hath undone: Or as the Lyon and the mans Daughter, in the <hi>Apologue:</hi> The Lyon ſought the Fathers conſent for his Daughter: Very willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaid the man, upon condition that you will ſuffer your Claws to be pared cloſe, and your Teeth taken out, leſt you hurt my tender Daughter: The Lyons extream love cauſed him to do ſo; and then demainding his Spouſe, was not only denied her, but, not being able to help himſelf, was knock't 'oth' head for his kind Condeſcentions. When the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf of its proper and natural Guards, then will the fair Diſcipline be monſtrouſly kind to it: and the event every man ſees. But what at length do they intend by their aenigmatical ſpeech of Coming up to us? Will they Renounce one branch of their Covenant? Will they for ever lay aſide one of the Cords of their Whip with ſix ſtrings? I have ſeriouſly asked and urged ſome of them, and could not get any laſting Conceſſion, any longer than they ſhall be enabled to exact the whole: And do we admire they ſhould, until that time, ſeem at leaſt ſatisfied with part? Let them name one thing, that for Peace-ſake for theſe Hundred years, they would give to us more than we had before; But very many Relaxations have been make already, and are we awhit the nearer? Or is it not then time to make a ſtop of Diſpenſations; when the Diſpenſation for a time ſhall be alledged againſt the Law, and Canon it ſelf? And it is no kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all (in their opinions) that ſuch Mitigations and Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance have been; but Extremity, Tyranny, Injuſtice, Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs, to reſtore the Priſtine force and vigour to Eccleſiaſtical Laws. Upon theſe and the like Conſiderations, I conclude with <hi>Tullie</hi> to <hi>Antonie.
<note place="margin">Cic. Philip</note> Quaeris quare pacem nolo? Quia turpis; Quia periculoſa; Quia eſſe non poteſt.</hi> Would ye know, why I will have no peace? Becauſe it is diſhoneſt, becauſe it is dangerous, and becauſe it cannot be. It muſt needs be diſhoneſt and diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe of the conditions required. For they having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſeparated themſelves from us, and ſtanding at that diſtance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104650:11"/>firmly, do caſt the odious termes of Extreams, upon them they have ſo left; and call their dragging us to them, their coming home to us; and their pulling us down to their pleaſures, their coming up to us. And that it is dangerous, appears from mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Tenets, interpreted clearly againſt their own temporizing Gloſſes; by their apparently wicked attempts and practiſes: And if there were no more then preſent ambiguous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John Cerbet's</hi> Intereſt of <hi>England.</hi> pag. 24. pag. 57.</note> and two-handl'd Phraſes whereby they Characterize themſelves, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh themſelves from others, they are much to be ſuſpected. For we often do hear them Magnifying their Capacities and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius's, as that they are Free-born Subjects; they are a free ſpirited People; a free-born People; and ſuch like: which as they are ſpecial pieces of flatteries to make the common ſort proud of themſelves, ſo truly, we cannot throughly underſtand what they ſignify: but this we know, ſuch Phraſes change like water, in Weather-glaſſes: If it be a fair and clear time with us, than do they fall down low, to a very tolerable ſenſe; but if fowl and troubleſome, then do they riſe to a higher Meaning a great deal, and Actions ſuitable. And what poſſibility of Reconciliation and Peace durable, is to be expected from thoſe men, whom nothing truly will content leſs, than their entire Diſcipline? but if they accept leſs for the preſent, they take it, only as men do debts hard to be got in, in part of payment, until they ſhall be able to recover all. Hear what the above mentioned Pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Moderator ſaith, and you will begin to ſee, what great hopes, or advantage may be had of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Publick State of theſe Differences is ſuch,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John Corbet's</hi> Intereſt. <hi>pag.</hi> 109.</note> that the Prelatiſts may, and ought to deſcend to the Presbyterians in the propoſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Way; but the Presbyterians cannot come up to the Prelatiſts in the hight of their Way. For the Prelatiſts Condeſcention, ſtands only in the omiſſion of certain things, which ſeem to them laudable; but the Subjection of the Presbyterians ſtands, in Subſcribing, and Conforming to certain things, which ſeem to them unlawful.</hi> Thus he. But, according to what Rule does it appear, which is here weakly and childiſhly taken for granted, that the <hi>Prelatiſts</hi> (as this <hi>Jack-ſtraw</hi> miſcalls thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) are ſo high? Let it be ſhewed, what is the Mean they have ſo far exceeded; and what Laws of Church-Government they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104650:12"/>have, or do Tranſcend? If they make their Interpretations of Scripture, the Law; their Models, the Rule; their Diſcipline, the Mean, we ought to compare, examine and judge our ſelves by, we muſt confeſs we are out; we are in the Extream, we are very high: but who could be ſo bold beſides theſe men, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch a fond and abſurd conceſſion? And who ſo ſtupid among us, to yield, to that moſt Ridiculous way of Tryal? when We being the only Legal Viſible Church of this Nation, as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Conſtitutions, in all equal Mens reaſon have a Right to judge them, and rather Condemn them of Extream, on the contrary ſide, to which, we neither can, nor ought to deſcend. But it will be ſaid, The Reformed Churches abroad may direct us. Ye are to know, and conſider, That there is not One Reformed Church that We can hear of, that (were it their Caſe, as it is yours) would thus tugg, and ſtand out againſt us: as Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel</hi> hath amply ſhewed. Again, Our Church hath no ſuch Obligations, to receive the Sentence of All the Reformed Churches put together; as you have, to ſubmit to Ours, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generally Educated in, and under the ſame. And Thirdly, I Appeal to all the World, What an unwiſe, and ungodly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it would be in us, ſo to condeſcend to your Pitch, and conceptions of Church-Government, and Orders for the gaining of a very uncertain Peace with you, and thereby put our ſelves out of a poſſibility, of having any Communion, or Peace with almoſt infinite Churches abroad; who will receive into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Fellowſhip, none that want ſuch things, as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us to lay away, for love of you. I ſpeak not ſo much of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> as <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern Chruches;</hi> with whom to hold Communion and Peace, by retaining ſuch Conſtitutions and Orders as we now enjoy, is ten times more deſirable, and Charitable, than for your ſakes to part with them. And we are aſſured, under your devices, we ſhall never obtain it. Furthermore, whence hath this Author, That they of the Church hold thoſe things only Laudable, wherein it differeth from <hi>Sectaries?</hi> And that it is not as unlawful according to our Conſciences to omitt them, as it is with their Conſciences to do them? We do not ('tis true) hold them to have any Moral Good in them, of themſelves, and therefore we call them Indifferent.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104650:12"/>And the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do not affirm they have any Moral Evil, and therefore grant they may be obſerved. There muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſomething more in the wind than Conſcience, on theſe Mens parts, which detain them: For as much as neither they, nor any man elſe, can pretend an Offence of Conſcience, where there is neither real, nor apparent Evil: but 'tis a contradiction that any thing ſhould ſo much as appear to be Evil, or Sinful, while it appears Indifferent. Therefore according to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> own Tenets, they may come up to us; for it can only be pretended to be againſt their Conſciences. And if they Alledg any Cauſe, why that, which in it ſelf is not Evil, nor againſt their Conſcience, may be, and is, upon another account, which 'tis eaſie to gueſs at; I will anſwer, That, juſt ſo it is with the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Many things which being not abſolutely, and in themſelves good, or neceſſary, and ſo conſequently may be omitted with a ſafe Conſcience; for certain adventitious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and Exteriour Accounts, no whit inferiour to thoſe of the other ſide, they cannot with a good Conſcience be Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, or Omitted. And thus we ſee the Vanities and Miſtakes in alledging Extremities, Moderation, Tyranny, and tender Conſcience, in theſe Caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A General determination of the Queſtion according to Reaſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat all Factions, Parties, Perſons, or Religions are not to be Tolerated, or granted Liberty; I think all agree. It will be neceſſary then in the Firſt place, to lay down certain Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſerving to judge of the reaſonableneſs of ſuch Inhibition towards ſome, rather than others. And they may concern either the Perſons or the Religion, or laſtly, the kind of Tolerations or Reſtraint, themſelves.</p>
               <p>Perſons pleading for Liberty of Religion are Firſt, either
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104650:13"/>ſuch as are of themſelves altogether Free from any Civil, or Moral Subjection from us, or ſuch as by Birth and Education being incorporated into the ſame Body, and Polity, are, and ought to be, ſubordinate unto the Head thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Religion Inſiſted on, and Pleaded for, is either Repugnant to the light and prime Principles of Nature and human Society, or Conſiſtent with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe all Reſtraint Moral, ſuch as is Diſſwaſion, Refutation, Excluſion from the Society of others, is by the conceſſion of all Parties inſufficient to ſuppreſs a growing Evil, oftentimes; and therefore outward Civil Mulcts, and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are in ſuch Caſe, to be Inflicted; the diverſity of ſuch Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is to be conſidered. For according to the Civil Law, Puniſhments are either Corporal, or Non-corporal. And Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, are either Capital, or Not-Capital, Puniſhment Not-Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral is that, which diveſts a man of any Profits, Emoluments, or Dignities. Corporal, and Not-Capital, is that, which is Inflicted on a mans Body, without taking away the Life. Capital, is that which deſtroyes Life. According to theſe therefore, it may be anſwered to the main Querie:</p>
               <p>Firſt, That it is not only Lawful and Reaſonable to allow a Toleration to Perſons in Co-ordination to us, and not depending upon us; But it is very unjuſt, and unnatural to attempt by Force, to reduce them to our way of ſerving God:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Humani ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; naturalis potestatis est, unicui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> quod putaverit cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; nec alii ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est aut prodest altertus Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio. Sed nec Religionis est cogere Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quae ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſuſcipi debet: non enim cùm &amp; hostiae animo libenti ſuſcipi expostalentur.</hi> Tertullianus <hi>Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>capulam.</hi> ca. 2. <hi>Vide</hi> Thomam 22. qu. 10. <hi>Artic.</hi> 8.</note> For ſuch kind of Force, or Violence, cannot be offered, but by Civil Power aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and Civil Power ought never to be exerciſed, but by Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority: and they, whom we ſuppoſe to be of diſtinct Societies and Regiments, can have no Legal right to Invade, or Uſurp upon one another. And this being againſt Juſtice (which alwaies is to be preferred before the beſt Religion) it would be a contradiction to advance and build Religion upon the Ruines of that which Founds all Religion: as <hi>Tertullian</hi> excellently argues.</p>
               <p>And if this holds good in Perſons Co-ordinate, ſo far that it is moſt unjuſt for Either, to impoſe upon Other their Faith, or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104650:13"/>Worſhip: it can ſcarce be expreſſed, the horrible Crime and Unjuſtice of them, who being as Legally Subordinate and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as tis poſſible for People to be, take the confidence to Arme, to the end, they may reduce their Prince, and Paſtors to the Rule of their Conſciences: And having oppreſſed both, though fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Main deſign, the Scene changed, to exceed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves in Immodeſtie, and demand that benefit, they would no wayes grant others, whom they had no right at all to deny; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſons infinitely Inferiour to them, they a while ſince rejected. In theſe ſhameful ſtraits, they ſay with one of their late Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>The Presbyterian Party in</hi> England,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corbet</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> pag: 57.</note> 
                  <hi>never engaged under a leſs Authority, than That of both Houſes of Parliament.</hi> Good Sir, clear up, and ſpeak out. Did they do well, or not, in ſo Engaging, even with both Houſes on their ſide? If they did well, then did we very ill, to Oppoſe and Reſiſt; Then were all your Enemies Rebells, the King himſelf not excepted: Then why do you not Preach Repentance to us, as we do to you? Then will you, then may you, nay, then ought you to do ſo again, as we profeſs we are bound to do, and alwayes did in our greateſt Perſecutions: And are you not well to be look'd to, think you? But your Caſe is ſtill worſe: For it will never be granted, what is here ſuppoſed. <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe Two Houſes were Houſes of Parliament, but a <hi>Conventicle</hi> of Private Men, after the Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Part of the Lords-Houſe which have been proved to be no leſs Eſſential to a Parliament than the remaining States, had they remained with the <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> but 'tis apparent, not the Major Part continued with them, but manifeſted againſt them: But eſpecially, the <hi>Kings</hi> Authority withdrawn from them, they like <hi>Sampſon</hi> the <hi>Nazarite</hi> being ſhaven, became as other men, and the Spirit of Power, and all Legal Authority departed from them. Or if after all theſe Ruines and Delapidations, they muſt ſtill be called Houſes; in what doth <hi>Presbyterian</hi> excel the following Factions, who had thoſe things, they called Two Houſes too, and with no more prejudices?</p>
               <p>But my Author proceeds, and indeed ſpeaks plainly.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id:</hi> ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>I have read</hi> (ſaith he), <hi>That the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>is of a Twofold capacity.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Repreſenting the People, as Subjects; and ſo, that it can do nothing, but manifeſt their Grievances, and Petition for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104650:14"/>Secondly, <hi>By the Conſtitution, it hath part in the Soveraignty; and ſo it hath part in the Legiſlative Power, and in the final judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> You have read. You may have read, and that from your own party, infinite paſſages of Sedition, and Treaſon: But had you ſo little Wit and Loyalty, pretending ſo much to both, as to Publiſh and approve it, and to juſtifie wicked Practiſes by as bad Principles? But they are in the Faction ſtill, and though like Water in a ſpunge or clout ſcarce diſcernible, when let alone, being preſſed a little, out they come. But muſt he that ſpeaks Treaſon, ſpeak Nonſenſe and Impoſſibilities too? For, 'tis not poſſible that the ſame perſons ſhould conſiſt of ſuch a Contradictory Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, as that of the Subject and Soveraign. But I return:</p>
               <p>It is worſe than Barbarous to Attach, or Oppreſs any People, meerly upon account of Religion, not repugnant to the Light of Nature, as I ſhall ſhew by and by: For otherwiſe, Religion, whoſe chief End is to Conſerve Mankind, in Peace and Juſtice, would turn the Earth upſide, down, and fill the World with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant Combuſtions, and Maſſacres. For it will be as reaſonable that the <hi>Infidel,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> ſhould Invade the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> upon that ſcore, as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Him. And then where will ſuch Depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations end?</p>
               <p>Again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thom.</hi> 22. <hi>Quaest.</hi> 10. <hi>Art:</hi> 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Iſidor. Peluſiot:</hi> li. 3. Epiſt. 362 <hi>Lactant.</hi> Lib. 5 <hi>Instit.</hi> ca. 19. <hi>Christus Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolos miſit ad ſeminandam fidem, qui &amp;c. Ambroſ. In Luc.</hi> Lib. 7. <hi>Pict. ad Constant. Joan: Duil: De Vero <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu Patrum.</hi> Lib. 2. ca. 6.</note> as <hi>Thomas</hi> hath obſerved, Religion being a Free Thing, there is no Reaſon <hi>Infidels</hi> ſhould be thereunto Compelled. Nay, as <hi>Iſidore Peluſiotes</hi> noteth well, To Force and Dragg others to the true Religion, who are abſolutely at their own diſpoſal; neither is, nor ſeems, Decent or Convenient. And <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non opus vi &amp; injuriâ, quia Religio cogi non poteſt.</hi> There is no need of Force and Injury, for aſmuch as Religion cannot be Compelled. And St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Teſtifies truly, That Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles to ſow the Faith, who were not to Compel, but Teach, nor to Exerciſe Force, or Power, but extol the Doctrine of Humility. And agreable thereunto St. <hi>Hillary</hi> writes, <hi>Deus cognitionem ſui docuit potius quàm exegit,</hi> God rather Taught, than Extorted the knowledg of himſelf. To theſe, and this effect, I might add ſuch Fathers as <hi>Monſieur Duillee</hi> hath collected; endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104650:14"/>though in vain, to prove thereby, that the preſent Church, hath fallen from the Opinions of the Auncient, becauſe they were againſt Compulſion in point of Religion; which, with what I have obſerved ſeeming to favour Liberty in Religion, is eaſily anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by diſtinguiſhing of Perſons educated in, and ſubject to a Church, to whom they never granted a Licenciouſneſs of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; from ſuch as were not under any Obligation of Obedience and Conformity to a Society: Of theſe they are to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and not of them: For herein they followed the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> who ſaies, <hi>What have I to do, to judge them that are without?</hi> And of theſe, are the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.12.</note> to be underſtood; abuſed by trifling <hi>Sectaries:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.13.</note> Thy People ſhall be willing in the day of thy Power.</hi> Which implies, a freeneſs of conſent to the Service and Faith of Chriſt under the Goſpel, in ſuch as firſt received the knowledge thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, According to the Second Diſtinction, it may be ſaid, that there being ſome Religions not only contrary to ours, but even to the Light, and commonly received Law of Nature; ſuch are not only, not to be admitted into any Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but it is Lawful for Chriſtians, or not Chriſtians, in vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Common-Laws of Nature, even ſuch, which being once and lightly offered to the Conſideration of ſuch as do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame, do in a manner conſtrain Aſſent thereunto; provided that Intereſt, Paſſion, and unnatural Vices, have not taken away that ſight, which Nature had given. For we know who ſaies, <hi>That the God of this World blinds the eyes of ſome:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4. 2 Pet. 3.5.</note> and who ſaith, <hi>Some things men are willfully ignorant of.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Actual Ignorance neither excuſes, nor exempts men from Puniſhment, even of ſuch, as are not in Political Authority over them. The reaſon whereof, is, Becauſe, however the World be divided into ſeveral Countries, and thoſe Countries ſub-divided into ſeveral Nations and Governments, abſolute in themſelves, as to Political Adminiſtration; yet, are All Men of the ſame Fleſh and Blood, and kind, and nature, yea, Common-wealth,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.26.</note> and Familie, as to certain Principles of Reaſon, and Nature, which are as Laws containing men in the ſame Society; and as to the Deſign that God had, in placing Man upon Earth, which was to live at leaſt ſo Humanely, as might continue the Work of Gods
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104650:15"/>hands upon Earth, and the Recognition of a Superior Cauſe of them, and Power and Dominion over them, which is a Deity; contrary to which, is that moſt brutiſh and degenerous Sin of <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> For though <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> be not a Religion (of which we now ſpeak), yet it is to be reduced to this Subject, as all Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are there to be handled, where their habits are properly treated of.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Diog <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aert: In Zenone.</hi> Epheſ. 2.12.</note> Now the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> (as <hi>Laertius</hi> tells us,) were wont to make a Two-fold <hi>Atheiſm; Dogmatical,</hi> whereby men not only know no God, but would prove, There is no God: And <hi>Practical,</hi> whereby men in general having a true, but weak, and obſcure knowledg of God, do, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>live as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World;</hi> as if there were no ſuch thing Exiſtent. But we ſhall rather divide <hi>Atheiſts</hi> into Purely Negative, ſuch as have, nor ever had, no knowledg of a God; and Poſitive, ſuch as have had the knowledg, and ſenſe of a <hi>Deity;</hi> and after, are fallen into ſuch open <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and <hi>Defiance,</hi> that they <hi>Dogmatize</hi> ſuch Unnatural Opinions. Of theſe Latter, we hold it juſt and reaſonable, that where they live mixt with other People who do revere a <hi>Deity,</hi> they ſhould be put to Death, after ſerious and plain Propoſal made of their Abominable Errors; without any laborious, or Learned controverting the Point. And this affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Perkins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkins</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.</note> before me, in theſe Words, <hi>As for thoſe that are commonly called</hi> Atheiſts, <hi>which deny that there is a God, they are to be puniſhed with Death, as not worthy to live in human Society; and the greateſt Torment, that can be deviſed by the Wit of Man, is too good for them: For, if they be holden for Traytors to an Earthly Prince, and are moſt deſervedly adjudged to Death, &amp;c.</hi> But I ſuppoſe, a greater reaſon than this, is, The certain Deſtruction which ſuch Embrutiz'd men do bring to human Society it ſelf: which, whoever is a direct and profeſſed Enemy unto, may be put to Death, as lawfully as Wolfs, Lyons, and Tygers. And yet, not at the pleaſure, or Power of every one that meets them, as wild Beaſts may, becauſe Judgment againſt the moſt open Malefactors condemned by the Law, muſt not be executed, but by Sentence, and Commiſſion from the Supream Power. For to make good one part of Juſtice, we muſt not deſtroy another; nor ſecure Gods Ordinance in one Point, by endangering it in another. But it is Gods Ordinance, that the Supream Power
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104650:15"/>ſhould be reſpected and obeyed; and it is ſcarce poſſible, that any Common-wealth ſhould be of any long continuance, where pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons take on them to adminiſter or execute Juſtice, upon their own preſumptions And if it be, as the wit of ſome <hi>Atheiſts</hi> lead them to conceive, that Religion is only a trick of Policy, to keep men in order, and obedience to their Superiours, and that they do confeſs, that it is neceſſary to keep together a Civil Society; do they deſerve any thing leſs than Death, who ſhall treacherouſly diſcover, and endeavour to Null ſuch a Myſtery of State, without which, Human Society cannot be maintain'd? And ſurely, if <hi>Chryſoſtom's</hi> zeal carried him ſo far,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matthaeus</hi> VVeſtmona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterienſis, <hi>pag.</hi> 182.</note> as to adviſe any one that met a Blaſphemer of God, or his Worſhip, to ſmite him preſently on the Face; yea, though he were ſure to be had before the Judg for ſo doing: it is more reaſonable to bait <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts</hi> and Perſecute them, the Supream Authority not gainſaying. <hi>Eſcobar</hi> tells us the Practice of <hi>Spain,</hi> to be againſt Blaſphemers, <hi>That for a Light Blaſphemy, he only abjures it: Yet, the Puniſhment doth anſwer the Sin.</hi> v.g. <hi>If they Blaſpheme out of ſuddain Anger, or ſome other Paſſion, they are Condemned to the Gallies: or elſe ſtanding bare Foot, and bare Head, girt with a Cord, and holding a Light Torch in their Right hand, they ſtand in ſome Feſtival day in the Church, and the Service being ended, they receive their Sentence with the reſt of their Penances,</hi> i.e. <hi>Faſtings, Prayers, and Pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie Mulcts.</hi> And where Authority is Defective and Remiſs, in this ſo horrible Provocation; It is obſerved by many dreadful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, how God himſelf taketh Vengeance: as, amongſt others, <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> tells us How, in the year of Grace 501, <hi>Olympus</hi> a moſt Mad Fellow, while bathing, he Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> that he was conſumed with a Fiery Thunder-bolt falling on him from Heaven. Thus he. And that, not only Corporal, but even Capital Puniſhment is due to ſuch an one, doth from hence appear; becauſe a man being of a Religion which aſſerts the <hi>Diety</hi> under ſuch and ſuch Forms,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cunaeus DeRe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>public. Hebrae. Li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Item Maimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in Miſna ractat. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus. ca.</hi> 9.</note> or Notions; the Profeſſed diſhonouring thereof, implies a ſelf Condemnation, and with all ſuch an unnatural humour of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, which leads him againſt all Religions, and human Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
               <p>And it is obſerved by <hi>Cunaeus,</hi> That ſuch was the Force of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104650:16"/>Seven Precepts of <hi>Noah,</hi> and extended ſo to all men, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were commanded, ſuch who were ignorant of them to ſlay by War, and remove them from human Society.</p>
               <p>Again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul. Apol.</hi> cap. 8. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. Civit. Dei</hi> lib. 7. ca. 19 <hi>Alex. ab Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and,</hi> lib. 6. ca. 26. <hi>Ludovic. Vives in Aug. de Civ. Dei. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. Grot. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Socin.</hi> pag. 200, 201, 202. <hi>Bod. De Repub.</hi> li. 1. cap. 5. 2 Kings 23.10 <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.33 36. Pſal. 106; <hi>v.</hi> 37, 38, 39. Jerem. 7.31. Selden <hi>de diis Syris</hi> Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag. 1. cap. 6. Porphyr. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 2.</note> it were (I ſuppoſe) Lawful for any Prince, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to compel any People that ſhould Worſhip their God, or gods by the Sacrifice of Mankind: And yet we read how far this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Superſtition prevailed over the World, as may appear from <hi>Tertullian, Auſtin, Alexander ab Alexandro, Ludovicus Vives, Grotius,</hi> and others. In a Word, Learned <hi>Bodin</hi> tells us, That there was never any People, or Nation, who imagined not, that the Gods might be pacified with human Sacrifices, ſuch as the <hi>Peruvians,</hi> and <hi>Braſilians</hi> at this day uſe: And, that the <hi>Canaanites</hi> in ancient days Accuſtomed themſelves to ſuch Sacrifices, <hi>Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sons and Daughters unto Molech, that Fiery Idol;</hi> the Scripture Teſtimonies are many, and expreſs; and not to be eluded, by the vain and bold gloſſes of Rabbies, attempting, I ſuppoſe, to extenuate the foul <hi>Apoſtaſies</hi> of their Predeceſſors; and that Children were not kill'd, and burnt, but drawn only through two Piles of Fire, and ſo conſecrated to <hi>Molech,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> hath obſerved out of them. But that <hi>Molech</hi> was the ſame with <hi>Saturn,</hi> and the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> offered to him ſuch inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Human Sacrifices, <hi>Porphyrie</hi> witneſſeth; which agrees per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, with the Practice of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> who themſelves, together with their Superſtitious Abominations, deſcended from the <hi>Phoenicians.</hi> For that the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> uſed to Offer ſuch Sacrifices;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Plutarch. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch,</hi> not only aſſureth us, but tells us who, and upon what occaſion, cauſed that Cuſtom to ceaſe. For <hi>Gelon,</hi> King of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> having Conquered them, would not make Peace with them, unleſs, they would firſt give over Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing their Children to <hi>Saturn.</hi> Poſſibly, this unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion took its Original from the Deſign of <hi>Abraham</hi> Offering up his Son <hi>Iſaac;</hi> which being performed amongſt the <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> might be cauſe of miſ-underſtanding to them, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable acts of the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Iſraclites,</hi> were firſt corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitated by the neighbouring <hi>Heathens,</hi> and by them tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and propagated into other parts: ſo that it was not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuggeſtion of Nature, though very common, ſo much, as Imitation.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104650:16"/>
               <p>Again, were it ſo, that any Nation ſhould freely admit, and practiſe the unnatural Sin, of Coupling with Beaſts after the manner of human Sexes; I doubt not, but it were Lawful, and Laudable in any Forrein Prince, to endeavour the aboliſhing of ſuch a Cuſtom, by Force of Arms, becauſe this is againſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, by confounding the Species of Man.</p>
               <p>In the Laſt place, according to our diſtinctions, we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the kind, and condition of Puniſhment to be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Offenders againſt Religion; of which, in the enſuing Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That the Ancients, as well Chriſtian as un-Chriſtian, conſtantly denied Toleration of Religions diſſonant and contrary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is a moſt frequent and plauſible Maxim which <hi>Sectaries</hi> have got by the end, to ſlip their Necks from the uneaſie Yoke of Government, and duty of Obedience incumbent on them, many times againſt their Wills and Intereſts; <hi>He is moſt a King, that rules in the Hearts of his Subjects; and that Prince is alwates beſt ſerved, and obeyed who by gentleneſs and kindneſs, gains the good will of his People.</hi> And this, though it hath much truth, ſoberly underſtood and modeſtly taken; yet, as by diverſe of late applied, includes in it a world of Knavery and Miſchief. For when will that be, that a Prince ſhall win the hearts of ſuch diſſatisfied, and fond Perſons as theſe, but when he ſhall lay the Scepter ſo lightly over them, as not to hurt them; when he ſhall give them ſo much Line, as that they may do what they pleaſe; when he ſhall remit, and relax the curbing and puniſhing part of the Laws ſo far, as that they may be dallied with, and played with at pleaſure, without Cenſure; when they may Inrovate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Phanſies of their own Brains, and Luſts of their Hearts: Such a King as this is fit to Rule over a Free Spirited
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104650:17"/>People, Free-born Subjects: and then ſhall he have their hearts when he requires nothing elſe, and can command nothing elſe. But me-thinks ſuch ſhould do well, to think ſometimes upon Rules of good Subjects: and that he is a good Subject (according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>) who doth all things [Lawful and Honeſt] without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and diſputing; and that makes a Conſcience of limitin; his Superiours in their commands, where God hath not Limited; and ſhould ſpend ſome of that time, and ſhew ſome of that Piety which they profeſs, in regulating and aſſiſting their Superiours, by their Precepts to govern them well, in putting in Practice the difficult Art of obeying Well; which Fleſh and Blood takes ſo little content in, that nothing is more ungrateful to them, and an unmortified carnal Man diſcovers himſelf in nothing more, than in that humour. But this, the Learning of the wiſeſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Experience, may teach us; that, as no Society of men can ſubſiſt without Laws, ſo no Laws without Coercion and Force; and no Coercion can take place, without Puniſhment. For as <hi>Tullie</hi> in <hi>Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> after him; All Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, continue, and reſt upon Two Principal Columnes, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and Benefits. For neither is Vertue ſo excellent and amiable in the eyes of all, no, nor Religion, nor Piety; as that men ſhould be ſo Raviſh't with their intrinſick beauty, as to need no External Motives to commend them to us, and excite our Affections; neither is there ſuch a loathſome Turpitude, or emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger in Vice,
<note place="margin">Plato in Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia.</note> Hereſie, or Impiety as that, no outward Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragments propounded, men of themſelves, muſt as neceſſarily Flee from them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca de C'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 21. <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ad tria reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picere debet. Aut ut cum quem pu nit emendet; aut ut poena ejus caeteros melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res reddat; au ſublatis malis ſecuriores caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri vivant. Galenw. Quod Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſequnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> &amp;c.</note> as they do from Serpents, or Mad-Dogs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> therefore aſſigneth Two principle Ends in puniſhing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors: Firſt, Satisfaction for the wrong done unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, by the Offence committed. Secondly, Prevention of like Miſcariages, by bringing a Terrour upon others. <hi>Seneca</hi> makes Three Cauſes of inflicting Puniſhment. Firſt, that the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may be amended. Secondly, or others corrected by their Sufferings. Thirdly, That the Evil being taken away, the Good may be more ſafe. Somewhat, not much differing from theſe, doth <hi>Galen</hi> likewiſe give Three Reaſons of Puniſhment. Firſt, leſt they ſhould miſchief the Good. Secondly, That a few being Chaſtiſed, others may be Reformed. Thirdly, That wicked
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104650:17"/>Men proceed not too far in wickedneſs: All which, hold no leſs in a Religious Commonwealth, than Prophane. For, what ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can the ſound Sheep be in, amongſt whom the corrupt and rotten ſhall be permitted to Walk? And what ſecurity can the Righteous and true Believer be in, ſo long as the Infectious Doctrine and Example of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> which do creep and eat like a Grangrene, whereby the whole Body is in great danger, to be diſſolved, and diſſipated.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.20.</note> And the Apoſtle adviſeth <hi>Timothy to rebuke them that ſin, before all, that others alſo may fear.</hi> It hath been therefore the conſtant practice of the Church of Chriſt, for the better conſerving it ſelf in Unity, and Charity; Firſt, to admoniſh and rebuke Litigious Diſſenters and Dividers; and, that not taking due effect, to proceed to ſuch ſevere Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as may render ſuch unable to Propagate their miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Tenets. And not the Church only, hath taken this neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe, but even <hi>Heathens</hi> have thought it neceſſary to deny a Liberty of Introducing new devices into Religion, to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and Diſſettlement of Others.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Valerius Max.</hi> li. c. 1</note> For <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> ſheweth how that certain Books being found in <hi>Rome,</hi> making againſt the Eſtabliſhed Religion; the City-<hi>Praetor,</hi> by command of the <hi>Senate,</hi> cauſed them to be burned. And <hi>Tullie</hi> tells us of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoras Abderites,</hi> that having wrot certain Books of dangerous conſequence to Religion, he was Baniſhed by the <hi>Athenians</hi> out of their City and Countrey, and his Books burnt in an open Aſſembly. And what is ſo manifeſt, as the ſore Perſecutions the <hi>Jews</hi> ſuffered under <hi>Antiochus</hi> for their Religion? and, How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and dreadful Perſecutions Chriſtians ſuffered under the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperors</hi> for the Faith of Chriſt? inſomuch, that it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by <hi>Polydore Vergil,</hi> and others; that from St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Polydorus Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil lib.</hi> 8. ca. 1. <hi>Invent. Rer.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Firſt, there being Thirty two <hi>Biſheps</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> all ſaving Seven, were <hi>Martyriz'd.</hi> But when Chriſtian Religion, partly by the Invincible Fortitude of Believers, and partly by the favour of ſome <hi>Chriſtian Emperours</hi> became ſo Publick and Root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and many were ſprung up from the Loyns of <hi>Chriſtian-Parents,</hi> ſo that they never taſted of Gentiliſm; it ſeemed reaſonable to that greateſt Enemy to Chriſtians, to conſtrain none to Gentile-Worſhip. For thus he writeth to one of his Governours. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Julian Epi.</hi> 52</note> 
                  <hi>We permit not that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104650:18"/>any of the Chriſtians ſhould be forced to our Altars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to draw nearer,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nec de Vet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ri Testam. profero exempla quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis etiam Propheticis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis doceri il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la dixisti. Il la, in quam, nimis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqua non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fero; fuerunt enim alterius diſpenſationis &amp; Temporis.</hi> Auguſtin. Lib. 4. <hi>Contra Creſcon: Grammat: Exod.</hi> 22. v. 21. <hi>Deuteron:</hi> 13.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron:</hi> 17.12:</note> I ſhall with St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> diſputing this againſt <hi>Creſconius,</hi> wave the Inſtances which may be brought out of the Old-Teſtament, becauſe they may be ſaid to be of a diverſe <hi>Oeconomie,</hi> from thoſe of the New. But moſt manifeſt it is, that ſuch as varied from the Religion in which they were Educated, were to be Cut off from their People; which I know is diverſely underſtood, but by All acknowledged to be a ſevere Puniſhment. And beſides it is undeniable, that ſuch as would not hear the Prieſts whom God had ſet over them in matters of Religion, were to be put to Death. Let us ſee what was the Practice of the Chriſtian-Church.</p>
               <p>Learned <hi>Pedro Paolo</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pedro Paolo Hidorie</hi> of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition. <hi>pag:</hi> 6.</note> ſeemeth to diſlike Perſecution for <hi>Hereſie:</hi> in that, treating of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> he argues againſt it from the Practice of the Church until <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great his time;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non invo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exemplum in Evangelicis &amp; Apostolicis Literis, altquid petitum à Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gibus Terrae pro Eccleſia. Quis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>egat non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventri. Sed non dum impleba tur illa prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Et nunc Reges intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Aug. Epist.</hi> 48.</note> ſaying, that until the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> i. e Three hundred and Twnety years after Chriſt, no Penalties were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon <hi>Hereticks</hi> But I cannot but marvel, ſuch a judicious Perſon ſhould take that to be an argument of the Churche's Opinion, That <hi>Hereticks</hi> ought not to be puniſhed; when as, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>Conſtantines</hi> daies, the Church was never poſſeſſed of any Civil Power; and it knew well enough it was againſt Chriſtian Religion to Uſurp it, though to the favouring and furthering of the ſame. But ſcarce was <hi>Conſtantine</hi> rid of that Tyrant, and Heathen, <hi>Lycinius,</hi> but, as <hi>Lycinius,</hi> out of Zeal, perſecuted the Chriſtians (which was the Ground of their quarrel, how ever malicious <hi>Zozimus</hi> Fables it otherwiſe,) <hi>Conſtantine</hi> endeavoured the ſuppreſſing of the Idolatrous <hi>Gentile-Worſhip,</hi> commanding (as <hi>Optatus</hi> telleth us) the <hi>Temple Doors</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to be ſhut up,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optatus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levita</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Contra Parm:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. Euſebius de Vita Constant.</hi> lib. 2. ca: 43, 44: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp; Socratis Hiſt.</hi> lib. 2. ca. 6. <hi>Nicephor.</hi> lib 8. ca. 25.</note> and that the Chriſtian Religion ſhould be only protected, and maintained Publickly. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, that he not only cauſed their <hi>Idol Temples</hi> to be ſhut up, but prohibited Sacrifices to them. And this his zeal did not end only in deſtroying <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104650:18"/>but extended to <hi>Hereſie</hi> alſo. For, after the Firſt Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had determined the Faith Controverted, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made it an Offence Capital, ſo much as to conceal <hi>Haeretick</hi> Books; as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> relate. <hi>Auſtine</hi> likewiſe, in an Epiſtle againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ſheweth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Augustinus Epist:</hi> 166 <hi>Donec Faelix ipſe juſſu &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> how after the <hi>Donat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts</hi>-Appeal to the Emperour, againſt <hi>Faelix</hi> who ordained <hi>Caecilianus,</hi> had been heard and rejected, by <hi>Helianus</hi> the <hi>Proconſul,</hi> and that he was declared Innocent, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Firſt, made a Decree moſt ſtrict againſt the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> and that his Son after him, followed therein his Steps, which continued until <hi>Julians</hi> Reign, who, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertor Chriſti &amp; inimicus, ſupplicantibus veſtris Rogatiapo &amp; Pontio, libertatem perditioni Partis Donati permiſit.</hi> An Apoſtate from Chriſt, and an Enemy to your Supplicants <hi>Rogatianus</hi> and <hi>Pontius,</hi> gave Liberty to the pernicious Sect of <hi>Donatus.</hi> And St. <hi>Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe</hi> makes it no ſmall matter of his praiſe of <hi>Gratian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſ. Epist.</hi> 26.</note> That he brought peace and quietneſs to the Church, and ſtopped the mouths (of <hi>Arians:</hi>)
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. De Fide lib</hi> 3. cap. 3.</note> and would to God (ſaith he) you could have ſhut the hearts of ſuch wicked men, and miſchievous; And that, this he did aſwel by the Faith, as his own Power. And no wonder that Father ſhould ſo write, who ſaith alſo, That <hi>Haereticks</hi> are more abominable, than the very <hi>Jews</hi> that crucified Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Histor. Eccleſ.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 16</note> And <hi>Theodoret</hi> relates at large, how <hi>Amphilochius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Iconium</hi> prevailes with <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> to exclude the <hi>Arian</hi> Conventicles out of the Cities. And <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> relateth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm. in Vita Theodoſ.</hi> pag. 285, <hi>&amp;</hi> 286.</note> that <hi>Hono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> publiſhed an Imperial Edict, whereby they decreed, that the <hi>Pelagians</hi> ſhould be wholly ſuppreſſed and expelled <hi>Rome:</hi> and after ſent their Reſcript to <hi>Aurelius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> in which they Commanded that they ſhould be driven out of <hi>Africa.</hi> And, as Cardinal <hi>Hoſius</hi> hath obſerved,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſius De Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio Oecomeu.</hi> cap. 24.</note> there is Extant amongſt the Proemial Epiſtles to the Council of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> an Epiſtle of <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the Empreſs to the Governour of <hi>Bythinia,</hi> to expel out of the City and Places where that Council was to be held, all Clergy-men, Monks, and Lay-men, who would by no means be brought to the Council. It is true,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bilſon,</hi> True difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>&amp;c. pag</hi> 19, 20.</note> what Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> hath obſerved, concerning <hi>Gratians</hi> Toleration of all, at his Firſt entrance into the Empire, That finding all places full of <hi>Arians;</hi> and the Laws of <hi>Valens</hi> his Uncle, making for them; Fearing ſome general Tumult, if he ſhould preſently diſtreſs ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104650:19"/>many, gave leave, that every Religion ſhould have Churches and Oratories, with freedom and immunitie; but being once ſetled and joyned with <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> he commanded that all <hi>Haereſies</hi> ſhould keep ſilence for ever. And this was the Courſe, as <hi>Beda</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth, which <hi>Ethelbert</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> King, took; who being convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Chriſtian Faith himſelf, gave order, that none of his Subjects ſhould be compelled to become Chriſtians; only he ſhewed them moſt favour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beda</hi> lib. 1. cap. 26. <hi>Hist.</hi>
                  </note> and kindneſs, who embraced that Faith which he did. And the reaſon hereof, is obſervable in the ſame Author, <hi>Didicerat enim &amp; à Doctoribus, Autoribuſque ſuae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis, ſervitum Chriſti voluntarium, non coactitium eſſe debere:</hi> For he learn'd from the Maſters and Authors of ſaving Doctrine, That Chriſts Worſhip ought to be Voluntarie, and not Compelled. But the Firſt of our Nation, That by Law deſtroyed Idolatry, was <hi>Ecombertus,</hi> in the Year, 640. who alſo commanded that the Faſt of 40. days ſhould be obſerved through his whole Kingdom. <hi>Quae ne facile à quopiam poſſint contemni, dignas punitiones fieri in tranſgreſſores juſſit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matthew Westmonasteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis.</hi> pag. 224.</note> ſaith <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> And becauſe it may be that ſome <hi>Hereticks</hi> will plead for favour, from the carriage of <hi>Ethelbert</hi> above mentioned, it is to be noted, that there is a vaſt difference between <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> who never had Knowledg of the Truth, as Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> hath truly noted, upon the like occaſion; ſaying, <hi>Hereticks of all ſects and ſorts,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bilſon</hi> Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſti-Subj. &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</note> may be compelled to follow truth, though Infidels might not; and ſo your Inference faileth when you ſay, No Law forceth Jews, or Pagans from their Perſwaſion, therefore not Chriſtians. Nay rather, if we grant Jews, and Turks excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for theſe two Reaſons, Lack of Knowledg, and Want of Promiſe; certainly, Papiſts being neither void of the Firſt, nor free from the Laſt, may, yea muſt, be compelled of Chriſtian-Magiſtrates, for dread of Puniſhment temper'd with good Inſtructions, to forſake their Hereſies, and forbear their Idolatries wherewith Chriſt is diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and his truth defaced.</hi> Thus he: Whereby their Plea is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made Void, whereby ſome argue from Toleration of <hi>Heathen,</hi> over whom there is no Authority, the Liberty due to Chriſtians, who do owe ſubmiſſion as well in general, by being Members of ſuch a Society, as particular by way of Promiſe, either Implicite, or Explicite; which each man makes to the Body,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104650:19"/>to which he is to conform in all Lawful things in themſelves; not meaſuring things Lawful by the Bent of our Conſciences (than which nothing can be more proudly contrived) but by the ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome Rule ſuperiour to them both. Whence it was, that <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> more ancient than the <hi>Nicene</hi>-Council, or <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted ſo far as he was able the <hi>Novatians,</hi> having no ſecular Power on his ſides; and ſo did other <hi>Catholick-Biſhops</hi> after him, namely <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for which ſome <hi>Puritans</hi> of our daies with a fellow-feeling, as it were, of their brethrens ſufferings, and a never failing Animoſity againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of all Ages, have not ſpared ſuch ſpeeches as theſe, againſt them. <hi>Chryſoſtome, whome none can ſufficiently praiſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Meditatio de Autipuritaniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</hi> pag. 70. <hi>Appendicis ad Laudenſium</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> took away many Churches from the Puritans; but this ſame violence was thought the Principal Cauſe, for which that moſt divine Perſon, ſuffering ſuch calamities as ſoon oppreſſed him, died in Baniſhment: Cyril likewiſe oppreſſed the Puritans</hi> [i. e. <hi>Novatians</hi>] <hi>and this man beſides many other evils and adverſities which he endured, as well at home as abroad, is branded with this note of Infamy, that he was the Firſt of all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that Lorded it;</hi> i. e. <hi>Introduced ſecular Pride and Tyranny into the Church. Let them beware, again and again, who in theſe daies bear deadly emnity with Puritans, leſt they pull upon their heads the ancient Puniſhments of the Perſecutors of Puritans.</hi> Thus far that Frontleſs, and Witleſs Patron of <hi>Puritans,</hi> of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Faction, if I miſtake not.</p>
               <p>And here before we draw down the Practiſe of the Catholick Church any lower, becauſe antiquity abounds with the like grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous complaints of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> being puniſhed, as this age doth alſo; Let us conſider a little what themſelves did, when ever their ſtrength ſerved them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arians,</hi> as we have ſhewed, were Perſecuted by the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> and having ſecular Authority on their ſide, did they not ſtir up moſt grievous Perſecutions againſt the Church, upon all occaſions? Are not all Hiſtories full of their Impious and Bloody Prancks? In ſo much,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Onuphrius</hi> in <hi>Sylvest.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Onuphrius</hi> on the Life of <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Firſt by <hi>Platina,</hi> ſaies, The Nine Perſecutions being taken away by <hi>Conſtantine the Great;</hi> the Tenth, from the <hi>A rians,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, more dangerous than all the others: which begining under the Emperor <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> continued upon the Church of God
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104650:20"/>in ſuch manner, for Forty years together. So far <hi>Onuphrius;</hi> Whoſe Opinion might eaſily be confirmed by the Authorities of <hi>Hilary</hi> of <hi>Poitiers, Hierome, Socrates, Theodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et,</hi> and others; were not that ſuperfluous Labour, in a matter confeſſed.</p>
               <p>And were the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> any whit more favourable, and mild when they had any, though but ſmall advantage, over the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks?</hi> He that reads <hi>Optatus</hi> againſt <hi>Parmenianus,</hi> the main Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> againſt them, the Conference of <hi>Carthage</hi> between the Schiſm of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and the <hi>Church-Catholicks,</hi> ſhall find, that the fame Faction which was ever moſt querulous under Perſecution, and moving pitty and compaſſion in thoſe that would hear them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Et maximè Epiſcopi &amp; Clerici horrenda &amp; dura perpeſſi quae commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare longum est quando quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam oculi extincti &amp;c</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin. Epiſt 5. <hi>Vide &amp;</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol. 166.</note> of their hard meaſure, and of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of the Civil Powers interpoſing in ſuch matters which ought to be free, were themſelves moſt Cruel and Violent againſt others; and eſpecially, the Biſhops and Clergy men ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed horrible things, which were tedious to rehearſe; putting out the Eyes of ſome; and they cutt off the Hand and Tongue, of one Biſhop, and ſome they ſlew right-out. I ſay nothing of the cruel Slaughters (ſaith he) and Plundring of Houſes by Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>invaſions, and Burnings; and that not only, of Private Houſes, but Churches alſo, into which Flames there wanted not ſome who caſt in the Books of God. Do not theſe words of <hi>Auſtine</hi> come ſomewhat near a deſcription of our late furious and wicked zeal. And what <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> in the Life of St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Poſſidonius <hi>in vita</hi> Auguſt. <hi>ca</hi> 9. <hi>Vide ca.</hi> 10. <hi>etiam.</hi>
                  </note> addeth of this nature againſt that Holy Biſhop, calleth to our minds afreſh, the Perfecution of the Tongue againſt our Biſhops: The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> (ſaith he) railed at <hi>Auſtine,</hi> called him Seducer of Souls, both Publickly and Privately; and ſaid, That he ought to be ſlain as a Wolfe to their Flock; and that without doubt all their Sins ſhould be forgiven them,
<note place="margin">Auguſtin <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistol.</hi> 68.</note> who could bring this to paſs. And in another Epiſtle of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is the Inhumanity of thoſe pure <hi>Zelots</hi> the <hi>Circumcellians,</hi> a branch of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> againſt ſuch as differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Opinion from them, deſcribed; concluding, <hi>In quibus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus illi non deponunt facta Latronum, &amp; honorem ſibi exigunt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum. i. e,</hi> In all which, they ceaſe not to act the parts of <hi>Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins,</hi> and yet require the honour of <hi>Martyrs.</hi> And, ſo infinitely Devilliſh and Malicious was their humour, that when they could not deſtroy the <hi>Orthodox</hi> by Butchering them, they would needs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104650:20"/>terrifie them, by Murthering themſelves; and ſo, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quidam eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum miſerabili instinctu, &amp; Deo &amp; Homiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ingrati, ſi ſuis caedibus nos vastare non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſſunt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uo nos exitio ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere credunt; aut laetitiam ſuam quarentes de mortibus nostris, aut tristitiam nostram de mortibus ſuis.</hi> Auguſt. Epiſt. 61.</note> either Solacing themſelves in the deſtruction of us, or ſadding us by their own Deaths. And ſuch in ſome degree, do our daies afford, who becauſe they cannot have their Will-worſhip, will put themſelves into ſuch an untractable and brutiſh poſture, that if you let them alone they have their ends, if you attempt to bring them to Juſtice, they will create great hatred to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, by parting with their Lives, rather than ſtir upon fair or neceſſary means, or motives. To conclude,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Legimus, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, quotid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> éque comproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; Quando perſecutio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Eccleſiam oritur, multo pejores perſecutores Judaeos &amp; Haereticos, quàm Ethnicos.</hi> Hieronymus <hi>in Obad. v.</hi> 10.</note> It is the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of St. <hi>Hierome, We have read, we have ſeen, we have daily found it true, that when ever Perſecution hath aroſe in the Church, the</hi> Jewes <hi>and</hi> Hereticks <hi>were alwaies more grievous Perſecutors of the Chriſtians than were the</hi> Gentiles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>A Continuation of the former Subject, and particularly, of putting</hi> Hereticks <hi>and</hi> Schiſmaticks <hi>to Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN man may be ſaid to be a Twofold Life, Natural and Civil. The Firſt is an Union of the Natural parts of a man; which being diſſevered, death follows; underſtanding here the principal which are either ſimply Eſſential, as the Soul and Body or ſuch, as are therefore called Vital, becauſe being corrupted, or taken away, a ſeparation of the more Eſſential parts do immediately follow. Mans Civil Life is that, wereby he being a member of the Civil Body, ſeparated from that (as all Integral parts of a Body Natural) lofe that life of common Influence and Protection. Hence it is, that ſome Civil Lawyers do interpret Capital Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo often denounced againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the Civil Law, of the later Death; as doth <hi>Huckleman,</hi> and ſome others. <hi>The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104650:21"/>Conſtitutions which abſolutely inflict Capital Puniſhment on</hi> Hereticks,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Constitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Imp. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er capitis poenam inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es Haereticis non de Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſed de Civili Capite aſſerit. Weſſembeck: in Vara.</hi> num 6. <hi>Huckelmanus Illustr. Difput.</hi> 34. Theſ 14. lit 6. <hi>God</hi> li. 1. Tit 5. <hi>God.</hi> li. 1 <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 5 <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Volumus eſſe publicum cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>are not to be underſtood of Natural, but Civil Death, as Tranſportation and ſuch like.</hi> But I make no doubt, but this is too favourable, and forced an Expoſition, as he that ſhall obſerve the Practice, the beſt comment on the Law, muſt confeſs. For when the Code ſaith, <hi>Manichaei undique expelluntur &amp; capite puniuntur.</hi> And immediately before, <hi>Manichaeo, in loco Romano degere deprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, caput ampuatur. i. e.</hi> The <hi>Manichees</hi> are to be expell'd, and puniſht Capitally, The <hi>Manichee</hi> that ſhall be found in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Territory</hi> ſhall have his <hi>Head cut off;</hi> cannot be meant of Civil Head. I confeſs the moſt common puniſhments, are ſuch, as we read in the ſame Title againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> made by <hi>Honortus</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Emperors. <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <q>We decree it a Publick Offence; becauſe an Offence againſt Divine Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is an injurie to all: wherefore we Perſecute ſuch with the Confiſcation of all their Goods. 2. We will likewiſe that they be Defeated of all Liberality and Succeſſion coming to them by any Title whatever. 3. Furthermore, we leave ſuch no Power to give, or buy, or ſell, or make bargains, being convict. 4. Inquiry ought to be made at his Death. For if it be Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in matters of Treaſon, to tax the memory of the dead; not undeſervedly ought there here alſo to paſs a judgment. 5. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his laſt Writing is to be Null, whether by Will, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicil, or any other way, he hath made his Teſtament; if found to be a <hi>Manichee.</hi> 6. Neither do we ſuffer his Sons to Inherit, unleſs they forſake their Fathers Errours. For we allow Pardon to the Penitent. 7. We like well, that they feel the ſting of our Authority, who ſhall entertain them in their Houſes, by a culpable providing for them. 8. And we Will, that their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be faultleſs, if avoiding ſuch Sacrilegious Maſters, they paſs into the Catholick Church by a more <hi>Faithful Service.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far the Imperial <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> whereby we may eaſily diſcern how ſevere the Ancients were in chaſtiſing <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and the ſeveral kinds of Puniſhments deviſed againſt them. But the great queſtion is, Whether it be juſt to puniſh <hi>Hereticks</hi> with Corporal Death, according to the Judgment of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church. The firſt inſtance of ſuch ſeverity, is that of <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillianus</hi> who was put to Death for his Hereſie: about which I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104650:21"/>find the Fathers themſelves divided. <hi>Hierome</hi> againſt <hi>Cteſiphon</hi> ſeems not only to approve of it himſelf, but to ſay, that the whole Chriſtian Church conſented thereto,
<note place="margin">Hierom. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid loquar</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de Priſcilliano, qui &amp; Seculi gladio, &amp; totius Orbis authoritate damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt?</hi> Why ſhould I ſpeak of <hi>Priſcillianus,</hi> who was Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Secular Sword, and the Authority of the whole World? But <hi>Severus Sulpitius</hi> liked not this Fact, as appears by his words,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Severus Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Sacrae Hist.</hi> Lib.</note> 
                  <hi>Priſcillianus cum ſoclis Capite plectuntur, peſſimo exemplo necati. Priſcillianus</hi> with his complices were beheaded, being killed with a very ill precedent. And <hi>Theognoſtus</hi> condemned <hi>Idacius,</hi> or <hi>Ithacius Clarus</hi> an eminent Biſhop of <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſidor. Hiſp. DeViris Illustr.</hi> ca 2.</note> as witneſſeth <hi>Iſidorus Hiſpalenſis,</hi> becauſe he procured the death of <hi>Priſcillian,</hi> as did alſo other Catholick Biſhops, as a bloody man: yet, by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil held at <hi>Triers,</hi> about the year 386.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Baron. An</hi> 386 nu. 25</note> he was abſolved by the favour and interceſſion of the Emperor <hi>Maximus,</hi> by whoſe Authority it was done.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. Epi.</hi> 48.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is known to have been of an opinion once, that <hi>Hereticks</hi> ought not at all to be Compelled to the true Faith; but afterward his judgment altered, and that (as he ſaith) from the experience he had of the excellent effect ſuch coercion had; and eſpecially, in that divers, who at firſt took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the profeſſion upon compulſion, afterward embraced it ſincerely and freely: And in the ſame Epiſtle, anſwereth the allegation of <hi>Pedro Paolo</hi> above mention'd, which the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> likewiſe urged againſt the <hi>Catholicks</hi> perſecuting them, <hi>viz:</hi> No example is to be found either in the Evangeliſts, or Apoſtles writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whereby any thing was begged of Earthly Kings in behalf of the Church, againſt the Churches Enemies.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Augustin. Epistol.</hi> 48.</note> 
                  <hi>Quis negat non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniri</hi> (ſaith he)? <hi>Sed nondum implebatur illa prophetia, Et nunc Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges intelligite &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 2. <hi>i. e.</hi> Who denies that? for as yet, that Propheſie was not Fulfilled, <hi>And now underſtand ye Kings, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id Epistol.</hi> 50</note> Yet do I not find, that this Father approved of killing <hi>Hereticks;</hi> but in another Epiſtle proceeds in a milder, and middle way, that is, Neither to Tolerate the <hi>Hereſie,</hi> nor Condemn the <hi>Heretick</hi> to Death; becauſe that were to cut off all poſſibility of Repentance, and Reconciliation to God, and the Church; which is very hard to deny any man, before God doth; And that God doth, no man can ſay, ſo long as he granteth him life. And to me, it ſeemeth not very difficult to anſwer <hi>Thomas</hi> his Arguments and <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> who are for the death of <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104650:22"/>
               <p>Thus then argues <hi>Thomas.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thom.</hi> 22. qu. 11 Art. 3.</note> If he may be burnt who counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits money, Why ſhould not he that Forges, and Publiſhes falſe Doctrine? <q>If he that counterfeits the Kings Letters deſerveth death, What doth he that counterfeits, that falſifies the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Divine Letters of the Lord? A woman that breaks the Conjugal Faith made to her Husband, ought to die; and not much more he, who keeps not his Faith with God? And he that takes away the Life of another unlawfully, ſuffers the loſs of his own for it; ſhall not he therefore who deſtroys his own, and neighbours Soul?</q> To theſe prety Analogies and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable arguments for the Death of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> we readily anſwer, by granting all that the arguments crave, which is, that <hi>Hereticks</hi> deſerve to ſuffer as much, and more if you pleaſe, than ſuch notorious offenders againſt the Commonwealth, and Civil Juſtice. But muſt therefore this puniſhment be neceſſarily corporal and outward as the other, whoſe cauſe is Civil? this, by <hi>Thomas</hi> his good leave, follows not. But rather the contrary. That their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſhould be Proportionable to their offence; Their offence was Spiritual, and their ſufferings muſt be ſuch too: their offence was greater, and ſo ſhall their puniſhment be in Soul by eternal Death.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm. De Laicis.</hi> li. 3. ca. 21.5. <hi>Probatur, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> And this anſwers <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſix arguments to prove, that <hi>Hereticks</hi> ought to ſuffer ſuch Capital Puniſhment. Firſt becauſe, as all confeſs, <hi>Hereticks</hi> may be Excommunicated lawfully, therefore they may be kill'd: The Conſequence is thus drove; Becauſe Excommunication is greater puniſhment than temporal Death. To which I anſwer, That therefore it ſhould have a greater death; but that, that death muſt be of the ſame kind, doth not follow, that is, temporal. Secondly, he ſaith <hi>Experience teacheth that there is no other remedie.</hi> But I deny any ſuch experience: For I make no doubt but the puniſhments mentioned even now in the Code, will in a ſhort time extirpate <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and perhaps ſooner, conſidering what a pride ſome <hi>Hereticks</hi> take in ſuffering, even death, for their errors. Thirdly, His Third is that with <hi>Thomas</hi> his, <hi>viz. Hereticks</hi> are Cheats and Counterfeits. And ſo is his Fourth taken from a Womans falſeneſs to her Husband. The Fifth is, becauſe All the reaſons that <hi>Galen</hi> alledged againſt Malefactors, hold here. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, That they ſhould be puniſhed, they do: Secondly, that they would be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104650:22"/>with death alſo, but not neceſſarily with Natural death; but Civil death may ſuffice here, and Eternal death hereafter. Sixthly, (Laſtly) he ſaith, It is a kindneſs to take obſtinate <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> out of this life: for the longer they live, the more Errours they deviſe; and increaſe greater damnation to themſelves <hi>Anſ.</hi> We muſt diſtinguiſh between temporary, and perpetual obſtinacy: And between that which may be, and is, certainly known to Judges for to be. Judges muſt proceed according to the Evidence of the Fact, not the probability. But no man can certainly know, that, how ever a perſon be Actually obſtinate, he will perſiſt in the ſame to his Death.</p>
               <p>But, notwithſtanding there be no more than we have heard in Reaſon, or Religion, for their putting to death, and not many examples are to be found in Antiquity; yet for the laſt Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ſince Chriſt, hath it been but too much put in practice under <hi>Roman</hi>-Tyranny. For that Hot-ſpur <hi>Genebrard,</hi> whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign it was to give us an account of the Churche's Practice, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in defence of that cruelty ſhewed againſt the <hi>Kathari</hi> (or <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi>) who were burnt at <hi>Colen,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1163.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Genebrard.</hi> Chronol: An: 1163.</note> meerly for Religion, and that none of the worſe; and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to juſtifie that Fact from ancient Precedents of the Church, could, it ſhould ſeem, find none much above 60. years older than that; and that was of that <hi>Arch-haeretick Baſilius</hi> a Phyſitian, who in the laſt year of Chriſt 1102 was by the Command of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Alexius</hi> burnt at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> for his <hi>Hereſie.</hi> But after-Ages abound with ſo many ſad Inſtances of that nature, that it were ſuperfluous and tedious to rehearſe them: From all which, I only inferr thus much: That they, who generally approved, and practiſed ſuch extream rigour, could not but much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſuch more moderate means of reducing, reſtraining, and extinguiſhing them. And I preſume, if I can ſhew what much more ſevere courſe hath been uſed towards <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> ſince our Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> it will not appear ſo great inhumanity, to put in ſtrict execution ſuch Laws as have of old and later dayes been made againſt them.</p>
               <p>In the Raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, ſaith <hi>Hollinſhed,</hi> were two <hi>Impoſtors</hi> hanged, for giving out, that they were Chriſts. In the Raign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104650:23"/>Statutes were made for the putting <hi>Hereticks</hi> to death, which ſtood in force until the Raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, who cauſed them to be repealed: but in lieu of them, he made ſuch an <hi>Edict</hi> (conſiſting of Six Articles, called therefore, The Whip with the ſix ſtrings) that thereby, the Life's Blood of many a good and ſober Chriſtian, was taken from them. But in the Firſt of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> the former Statutes, as more for her Bloody purpoſes, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived and re-inforced: of which, as a thing too apparent for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence it ſelf to encounter, I ſhall not ſpeak at preſent, and but touch afterward.</p>
               <p>But neither have there been wanting inſtances ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of ſuch Capital Puniſhments executed. For in the Fourth year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, or Third (as Mr. <hi>Stow</hi> hath it) <hi>Joan Butcher,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stow Chron.</hi> Ari. 3. <hi>Edw</hi> 6</note> otherwiſe called <hi>Joan Knell,</hi> and vulgarly <hi>Joan</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> was burn'd for her <hi>Hereſie,</hi> denying Chriſt to have taken Fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> And on the 24th. of <hi>April,</hi> the ſame year, <hi>George Paris,</hi> a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield</hi> for <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm:</hi> And in the ſame King's Raign, an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> of <hi>Cholcheſter</hi> was burned. And truly, he that is of an Opinion, that no man ought to ſuffer death purely for Religion, may notwithſtanding approve of the putting to death, ſuch as ſhall bear falſe witneſs, in ſuch a Caſeat leaſt, as that of profeſſing themſelves to be that Perſon they in truth are not, whereby manifeſt and intolerable evils are done to private Perſons, but much more to the Weal-Publick; when one ſhall pretend himſelf to be ſome Prince, or Publick Perſon: Much more therefore he that ſhall have the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to give out that he is Chriſt (have he a particular <hi>Cant</hi> of his own to evade the common ſenſe his words import, when he comes into danger) ought no leſs to undergo death, than he that ſhall ſeek to Tranſlate the Government of a People, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to another Prince, upon himſelf. And as for <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> though I think their Dogm's are a little purg'd of late, over what ſome years ſince they have been, (as moſt <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> are, when they perceive they will not take, nor be endur'd in their original Rankneſs): yet, if they ſtick but to one or two, charged commonly on them, ſuch as are, Denying to the Civil Magiſtrates, Power of the Sword; and affirming an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of (their) Saints from human Laws; ſuffering corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104650:23"/>death for the ſame, they have no wrong done them; neither can they plead Religion to protect them in cauſes of Civil cogniſance, as they are. And to hold an opinion (as many now adays do) that their Governors have no Authority Eccleſiaſtical over them, in things nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forbidden nor commanded by God's word, is to draw very much nearer to the pernicious Extreams of the <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> than can conſiſt with the good opinion ſuch have of themſelves, and would beget in others of being very moderate Men. But I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>In the third of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> one <hi>Jeffrey</hi> taught publickly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stow An.</hi> 3d. <hi>of Qu. Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>John Moor</hi> was Chriſt; who were both firſt whipt, and then upon repentance were committed to Priſon for half a year. This was a favour ſhown upon repentance. The more pittiful and ſtrangely tender conſcienc'd Judges were they in the Houſes called a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of late years, who could diſcharge <hi>John Naylor</hi> an Impoſtor, as foul and blaſphemous as any of his Predeceſſors, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable notes of true repentance. So far did the Doctrine of Liberty of Conſcience drive many Patrons of it.</p>
               <p>Again, in the Seventeenth year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stow in Eliz.</note> twenty-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were brought to juſtice, whereof two were burnt in <hi>Smithfield;</hi> four renounced their Hereſies at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſs, and thereupon were releaſed, the reſt were condemned to die, but were only baniſhed. In the twenty one year of the ſame Queen,
<note place="margin">Id.</note> one <hi>Hammond,</hi> a moſt inſolent <hi>Arian,</hi> denied Chriſt to be God, and blaſphemed Him, and the Goſpel, and was burnt in <hi>Norwich:</hi> And about three years after, one <hi>John Lewis</hi> was burnt in the ſame place for the like Hereſie. And in the Raign of King <hi>James</hi> one <hi>Legate</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield</hi> for <hi>Arianiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For King <hi>James</hi> his Raign, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth's,</hi> it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known how they put not any Papiſt to death for their Religion, though preſently they were Sainted for dying in the <hi>Roman</hi> cauſe, and, as they will have it, for Religion; and if they will have it ſo, ſo let it paſs, for me: But then we muſt take leave to turn to, and adhere to our old Notes, which tell us of their Faith, that it is Faction; and their Religion, Rebellion. For, were it ſo that the Laws interdicting <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prieſts of this Nation, bred and ordained beyond the Seas, from coming into this Nation, this were no ſuch ſanguinary practiſe as many Popiſh Miniſters loudly and indeed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104650:24"/>childiſhly give out. For I would know whether the Supream power of this, as well as any other Nation, have not power to inflict the puniſhment of baniſhment upon lighter cauſes than this? For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Might it not be reaſonable for an Act of Baniſhment to take place upon all ſuch as ſhould tranſport Wool, or Fuller's-earth into foreign Countries? The perſon that ſhould do this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns into <hi>England,</hi> and is put to death, according to the Law. But he cannot be ſaid to be put to death for having tranſported prohibited Commodities, but for breaking the Law of his Baniſhment. No more can Popiſh Prieſts, taking Orders from that Church, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, be ſaid to ſuffer for taking Orders, or for their Religion, but for breaking the Act of their Baniſhment; for, by Law they all ſtand baniſhed; and if a greater puniſhment than baniſhment be not annext to that Decree to make it good, inſtead of being ſanguinary it will become ridiculous and ludicrous, and ſo will the Authors of ſuch Laws alſo. In the year, One thouſand, ſix hundred, forty and one, <hi>Ward, Walker,</hi> or <hi>Waller</hi> (for, as I take it, the man after the <hi>Roman</hi> cuſtom had three or four names) being a Popiſh Prieſt was hanged at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> where he confeſſed, he had been baniſhed no fewer than three or four times. Do not ſuch mockeries and contempt of Laws as this, deſerve death, yea, though the Law it ſelf were unreaſonable?</p>
               <p>And now, as to the other ſide, with which we have to do, the <hi>Puritan</hi> Faction; let us ſee how they have been proceeded againſt, before theſe three laſt Decads of years, and whether it be ſo new and ſtrange a matter that they ſhould be moleſted, or oppreſſed; and the rather becauſe of that Officious Author of the <hi>Intereſt of England,</hi> who puts on the Countenance of a Moderator, and grave and wiſe decider of the point of Toleration: but alas, beſides his many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable failings, he could not keep on his Mask above a leaf or two; and in a certain place ſpeaks thus, much more boldly than knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or truly.
<note place="margin">Corbets <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, pag</hi> 129.</note> 
                  <hi>Take notice that the Epiſcopal Clergy did not go ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut to exterminate the Puritans before their latter times; and then he that had half an eye could diſcern the notable advance and the confiden ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Popiſh Faction.</hi> And may not he that hath never a bit of an eye perceive what is ſo palpable, that ſince the Puritans had ſuch influence, and favour ſhown them as of late, that the Popiſh Faction is advanced ten times more than when they were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104650:24"/>better kept under? And, this partly through the infinite ſcandal given to our Reformation by them; partly, forſooth, that for their tender Conſciences ſake ſuch an indulgence and connivance general muſt be allowed, that Papiſts (who have no leſs to ſhow for a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration than have they) muſt be comprehended in it too. But what doth this Man mean to write ſo at a venture? but that which moves them all, prevail'd with him; <hi>viz.</hi> that the common people would not trouble themſelves ſo far as to ſuſpect what he ſays, while he ſpeaks what they would have him. What think you of thoſe that Doctor <hi>Crackenthorp</hi> ſays againſt the Fugitive Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Crackenthor. <hi>Defenſio Eccl. Anglicanae Con. Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe. Spa. cap.</hi> 33.</note> (who for that reaſon, that Puritans were tolerated in <hi>England,</hi> took a prejudice againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi>) were perſecuted for their Conſciences? Was not <hi>Cartwright</hi> caſt into Priſon? Was not <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> degraded, and put from his Prieſthood? Were not <hi>Wigginton, Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwell, Salesbury, Field, Hilderſh. Parker, Stoughton, Smith, Jackson,</hi> and others, turned out of their Livings, and ſuſpended from their Prieſts Office? <hi>Udal</hi> and <hi>Penry</hi> adding to their obſtinacy revilings of the Queen's Majeſty, one of them was put to death, and the other received capital ſentence, and was puniſhed? Were all theſe or any of theſe of ſo late ſtanding as you mean? Do we not hear of moſt lamentable complaints of old, made by the Puritans, of the ſore perſecution they ever ſuſtained, and do they now accuſe later times, holding the former innocent?
<note place="margin">Fuller <hi>Eccleſi. Hist.</hi>
                  </note> The Letters between the Lord <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> are yet extant, whereby it appears that there were very many Miniſters turn'd out of their Benefices in thoſe days, in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> only for ſcrupuling the Rites and Ceremonies of our Chvrch. And more for the ſatisfaction of others, who are apt to think Civil ſeverity too much for the Church to have on their ſide againſt ſuch Men as theſe, than for this Authors ſake;
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>George, his Life of Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVhitgift. pag.</hi> 40.</note> Conſider what Sir <hi>George Paule</hi> writes in the Life of Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> and we ſhall be eaſily convinc'd that our Church acts no new thing, nor the Civil Magiſtrates ſo much as was wont to be done in behalf of the Church in the earlier days of Reformation. <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> and <hi>Edmund Snapo,</hi> with others, were called in queſtion, and proceeded withal in the Star-Chamber for ſetting forth and putting in practice, without warrant or Authority,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. pag.</hi> 54.</note> a New Form of Common Prayer, Adminiſtration of Sacraments and Presbyterial Diſcipline in the year 1591. Again, the Queen was offended that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104650:25"/>
                  <hi>Cartwright</hi> ſhould preach without Subſcription. Again, Good exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Laws (his own words) againſt Puritans kept things quiet;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. pag.</hi> 55.</note> eſpecially by the aſſiſtance of the Lord Chancellor <hi>Hation.</hi> And had he who ſo lately bare that name and office dealt more ſincerely and uprightly towards the Church, I ſuppoſe he had had no more to anſwer for, either before God or Man, than now he hath. Again, he proceeds.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. pag.</hi> 58. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
                  </note> After him, Sir <hi>John Puckering</hi> was a friend to the Church. And laſtly, Sir <hi>Thomas Egerton</hi> Lord Keeper was very careful to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the foreſaid <hi>Libels.</hi> And thoſe Libels were none other but the religious ſtuffe invented and vented againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Aſſerters thereof.</p>
               <p>And this may ſuffice to have ſhown what the ancient Churches judged of Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, and the allowance of them, and what our Churches hath done in reference to them. It is now more than time that we come to ſhew what both the opinion and practiſe of both of them have been towards us, that ſo, if there be remaining any Candor in the breſts of theſe importunate demanders of the ſame, they may bluſh to require it, or at leaſt, give us leave not to bluſh to deny the ſame. And the God of all Juſtice do that which is right in his eyes between us. And firſt let us hear the Papiſt, as briefly as the cauſe will permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Papiſts directly and abſolutely againſt Toleration of many Religions, or any beſides their own.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE have ſhewn out of <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> already, that Hereticks ought to be put to death, and why; and he that will be further ſatisfied therein may eaſily turn to Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators on <hi>Thomas,</hi> and find his opinion confirmed and juſtified, without any further trouble here undertaken, to the drawing out this diſcourſe to a length more tedious, than neceſſary to the Reader. Only from hence we may infer, what is a manifeſt conſequent to what hath been ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> That if ſuch may be cut off ſo by the Secular ſword, they, according to ſuch mens judgment, may and ought to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104650:25"/>be reſtrained and ſuppreſſed by puniſhments of an inferior rank,
<note place="margin">Johan. Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettus <hi>Praefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad Regiam Majestatem: apud</hi> Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phredum <hi>Admonit: de Curiae Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae praxi; contendit, de Evangelicis poſſe, de Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manenſibus non poſſe ſumi ſupplicium.</hi>
                  </note> and milder nature; unleſs it be ſaid by Papiſts (as in truth it is by ſome) what the Presbyterians ſay for themſelves, as we have ſhewed, That Prelatiſts may and ought to come to the Presbyterians, but the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians cannot, nor ought to come to the Prelatiſts; That puniſhment ought to be taken of the Evangelical [Profeſſors] that is, the <hi>Reformed,</hi> but the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ought not <hi>to be puniſhed.</hi> So De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative are the reaſons, and ſo ingenuous are the writings of both Papiſt and Puritan. But we muſt not altogether be guided by ſuch Oracles as ſpeak ſo broadly and vainly; if there be any ſuch thing remaining or to be reſpected in the World, ſure this is reaſon that Mens teſtimonies ſhould conclude againſt themſelves, when there is nothing but diſadvantage to them which make their caſes different. For, neither the one nor the other can modeſtly deny the Principles and Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be leſs incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Civil Government, and not ſo rank in perſecution of opinions differing from it, as are they; and yet forſooth they, where they cannot perſecute, muſt not be perſecuted, or touched; where they can, muſt not be queſtioned. Now that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> will not endure anycompetition in Religion, appears by what is ſaid above; and by theſe ſeveral inſtances.</p>
               <p>In the year of our Lord Five hundred fifty five, as <hi>Funcius</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">Hic Hereticos &amp; Schiſmaticos no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entes ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorem Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam reduci rationibus, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culari manu coerceri poſſe definivit. Funcius <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Chronol. lib.</hi> 8. Ribadeneira <hi>de las virtudes del Principe Christiano lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.26, 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Pelagius</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in the room of <hi>Vigilius,</hi> by the Emperor <hi>Jeſtinian.</hi> This Man (ſaith he) defined that Hereticks and Schiſmaticks who refuſed to be brought home to ſound Doctrine, were to be reſtrained by the Secular Power. And that this hath been the currant judgment of that Church, their Modern writers declare. Do they not make this Defence of theirs, and Offence of their Enemies Religion, one of their Firſt Principles and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments which they ſeaſon Princes with? Let the Work of <hi>Riba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneira</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> ſpeak for all. In the year 1597 he wrote a Treatiſe in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> Printed at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> Of the Virtues of a Chriſtian Prince; The Subjects of ſome of the Chapters of which Book, are theſe. <hi>That it is impoſſible, that Hereticks and Catholicks</hi> ſhould make a good League, in one and the ſame Commonwealth. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24. Examples of Certain Emperors, who ſuffer'd not many Religions. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. The ſame is proved by the Authority, and Examples of Saints. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. That <hi>Hereticks</hi> ought to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104650:26"/>and how prejudicial Liberty of Conſcience moſt be, <hi>Chap.</hi> 27. That <hi>Hereſies</hi> are the Cauſes of Revolutions and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of States. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28. From ſuch Titles as theſe, it is eaſie to divine, what is contained in that Work: I have thought good to leave all to the ingenuity of the Reader to judge, rather than to exceed in unneceſſaries.
<note place="margin">Becanus <hi>De Fide Haeret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>is ſervanda, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Paraeum.</hi>
                  </note> To this Author, let us add one of the ſame Fraternity, <hi>Becanus,</hi> in a tractate againſt <hi>Paraeus:</hi> where he lays down this as a Second Principle, <hi>Liberty of Religion and Faith is unlawful, and contrary to Chriſtian Doctrine, and hurtful and pernicious to the Commonwealth.</hi> His Reaſons are theſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe, as Divines teach very right, <hi>Hereſie</hi> is a greater ſin than <hi>Adultery, Murther,</hi> or <hi>Theft. Secondly,</hi> The Doctrine of Chriſt is true: But true and falſe, are contrary. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is hurtful: <hi>Firſt,</hi> In reſpect of the Salvation of Souls; <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> In reſpect of outward Peace and Tranquillity: For this cannot be preſerved without Unity of Faith.—<q>A third Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his is this, A Catholick Prince can neither preſcribe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, or introduce Liberty of Religion, but muſt hinder the ſame, as much as poſſibly he can. But yet, if he cannot hinder it without greater dammage to the Publick good, he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, as the leſs Evil:</q> Hitherto <hi>Becanus.</hi> And that very Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain <hi>Parſons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Parſons</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 <hi>num.</hi> 5.</note> in a Treatiſe of Mitigation, writeth thus, <hi>We agree with the Proteſtants in this, that there can be no agreement between us and them in Religion.</hi> Yea, ſo far did this mans Zeal hurrie him for Religion, who himſelf was by his own ſide ſuſpected to be an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> in heart, that preſuming at length by his many State-Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, and Treaſonable Practiſes, to ſubvert both Church and State, as they were then eſtabliſhed, that one of his requeſts to the <hi>Pope</hi> was, That <hi>England</hi> being reduced to his Model, none other <hi>Popiſh</hi> Orders might be Tolerated in <hi>England</hi> ſave the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> which were not like to diſagree ſo much as <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> with other Orders and the <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> while theſe kept to their particular Rules of having all they can lay their hands on, and they of having nothing. And I have been told, that even ſince the Reſtauration of his Preſent Majeſty, the Emulation and Animoſities have been ſo great, that after ſeveral Pamphlets, For, and Againſt <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prieſts</hi> with the aſſiſtance of ſome of other Orders under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104650:26"/>with ſome Great Perſons that, upon condition they might have a Toleration (which is the moſt that any Faction did at firſt Petition for) they would take care, that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be admitted in <hi>England:</hi> of which, Mr. <hi>Creſſie,</hi> that buſie <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> can give you a farther account. But when a man conſiders how that ſubtil, induſtrious, and powerful Faction hath bafled all the ſevereſt <hi>Edicts</hi> againſt them in ſuch Countries where <hi>Popery</hi> flouriſhes, he will ſcarce believe that ſuch a device could take effect, or, if it did, could continue long. Could any Decree be more ſolemn, or ſharp againſt them, than that, made by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> whereby, the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> were all to depart <hi>Paris</hi> within Three daies, and within Fifteen,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1594</note> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the whole Kingdom; and a Pillar to be erected in Publick, for Poſterity to read their wickedneſs and doom; for the Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſination of that Great Prince in his own Chamber, by a young bird <hi>John Chaſtel</hi> of about 18 years of age, of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up: And yet, ſuch was their Dexterity, Diſſimulation, and Intereſts with <hi>Pope</hi> and all <hi>Princes</hi> of their Religion, that about Ten years after, the very ſame King ſhould be impoſed upon ſo far, as to demoliſh the Monument of their Wickedneſs; repeal his Banne, reſtore them again: And in the very ſame year (as moſt then, and there living, judged) the ſame King being Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered right-out by <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> inſtigated by thoſe holy men; they not only eſcaped cenſure, but carried the matter with ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice, that the Kings heart muſt be given to them, as his beſt Friends; and conveighed to a Convent of theirs at <hi>La Flech:</hi> Notwithſtanding, thus much <hi>Ravilliack</hi> confeſſed (who would confeſs but little) that by reading <hi>Mariana</hi> the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Book, he was impelled to commit that Fact: Whereupon <hi>Cotton,</hi> the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> Chief Father, wrote a Book to the Queen, endeavouring to ſhew, that they held no ſuch opinions: But another Author wrote a Book, which he entituled <hi>Anti-Cotton,</hi> wherein he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly proved the contrary.</p>
               <p>And did not the State of <hi>Venice</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifths time, upon diſcovery of their treacherous, and miſchievous Prancks, expel them their Dominions, adding a Law after them, which made it Death for any, to propound any thing to the <hi>Senate,</hi> in order to their Return; yet have they ſo brought it about, by the <hi>Pope</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104650:27"/>their ſingular Friend; and by the <hi>Turk</hi> their happy Enemy; and laſtly, by their infinite Treaſure, That admittance and welcom is granted them into their Countries.</p>
               <p>But to return: Judg we yet farther of their Opinions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Toleration of others, from that prophane Fop, Author of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 260.</note> who, in a good humour, profeſſes great kindneſs to both <hi>Prelatical</hi> and <hi>Puritan Party;</hi> but that forced fained Part being ſoon laid down, and he returning to himſelf, compares them both to the Bond-maid, and her Son <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs will ſatisfie him, than, <hi>ejice Ancillam cum Puero ſuo.</hi> Out with them both; Surely that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> may enter, and have not only free, but alone Poſſeſſion! For he adds; This is the only remedy and means of Peace.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> where we above quoted him, gives us not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his opinion, but reaſons, why <hi>Hereticks</hi> may not be ſuffered, which are worth the reciting on this occaſion. This then is the ſubject of one Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm:</hi> li. 3. <hi>To.</hi> 2. ca. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Non poſſe conciliari Catholicos cum Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis, i. e;</hi> There can be no Reconciliation between <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks:</hi> And whom he means by both, no doubt is to be made. Firſt, then he begins with <hi>Caſſander,</hi> and quarrels with, and confutes him: whoſe opinion, and deſign he tells us it was, That Princes ought to find out an Expedient toreconcile <hi>Catholicks, Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts:</hi> and that until this could be effected, every one ſhould be permitted his Faith; provided he received the Scriptures and Apoſtles Creed. But herein the Cardinal was miſtaken: For in that Treatiſe, <hi>De Officio Pii Viri, &amp;c.</hi> quoted by him, <hi>Caſſander</hi> has neither any ſuch words, nor deſign: but this muſt be rather found in his Conſultations; and even there, he doth not propound any thing for the Toleration of diverſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, but the reduction of Religion to Primitive Rule of Holy Scriptures, Interpreted by pureſt Antiquity, which was the moſt equal, and viſible outward means of Reconciling Differences. But his Reaſons, why neither <hi>Lutherans,</hi> nor <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ought to be Tolerated, becauſe they are ſuch for the moſt part, that War againſt himſelf, and Pretenders to Moderation at preſent; we will here ſet down. Firſt, becauſe we agree not in the Creed it ſelf. Secondly, <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> are no true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church. Thirdly, <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> differ
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104650:27"/>more, than in Rites; in ſuch things as are of greateſt moment, and yet not contained in the Creed it ſelf. 4. The Holy Fathers, and the Apoſtles, require that we ſhould obſerve not only the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, but leſs Matters. 5. If it be free to believe as men pleaſe in one point, by the ſame reaſon they may be ſuffered to believe ſo in others alſo. 6. This is a new opinion of <hi>Caſſander,</hi> and therefore to be ſuſpected. 7. This opinion renders the Church altogether obſcure and inviſible.</p>
               <p>And in his 21th. Chapter propounding this ſubject, <hi>Poſſe Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos ab Eccleſia damnatos temp ralibus poenis, etiam morte, multari:</hi> He firſt tells us how <hi>John Huſs</hi> at the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> affirmed that it was not lawful to deliver incorrigible Hereticks to the Secular power, and ſuffer them to be burnt; and how <hi>Luther</hi> affirmed the ſame, and that it is no new error; for as much as the Donatiſts held the ſame: after all this he adds, <hi>Contrarium docent omnes Catholici, &amp; aliqui etiam Haeretici;</hi> i.e. All Catholicks teach the contrary, and ſome Hereticks; of which ſort is <hi>Calvin,</hi> who cauſed <hi>Servetus</hi> to be burnt at <hi>Geneva:</hi> and ſo <hi>Aretius</hi> cauſed <hi>Valentinus Gentilis</hi> to be put to death at <hi>Berne.</hi> You may ſee his <hi>Theſis</hi> proved afterward by ſeveral places of the Old and New Teſtament, which I liſt not here to relate; they are obvious of themſelves. <hi>Stapleton</hi> in his Sermons confirmes this ſaying, <hi>Qui libros Haereticorum legere, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Staplet. <hi>Prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta Moral. Domin</hi> 7. <hi>post Pente.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q>They who think it no ſin to read Hereticks Books, or ſuppoſe they may be ſuffered ſafely, conſider not what that imports which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſays,</q> 
                  <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> And to imprint this the better in our minds, he tells us with great gravity and ſeriouſneſs, a Tale out of the common Budget, thus. 'The Abbot <hi>Cyriacus Presbyter</hi> of <hi>Laura Calamon,</hi> near the River <hi>Jordan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pratum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. cap.</hi> 46.</note> ſaw in his ſleep <q>the Bleſſed Virgin paſs by his Cell; and being very importunate with her that ſhe would vouchſafe to come in [and ſurely to take an hard bed] ſhe replied. How can I enter into thy Cell while thou keepeſt by thee mine enemy? and, ſo having ſaid thus, went her way. But he waking, marvelled what this ſhould mean; but at length having ranſacked all his Cell, he found two Books of <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> ſtitched to a Volume of <hi>Jſychius.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <note place="margin">Surius <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar-rerum gectarum in Orbe. Au.</hi> 1540 <hi>pag.</hi> 400.</note> Anſwerable hereunto is the applauſe given by <hi>Surius</hi> to the Emperor's Decree made in the year 1540. for the burning of Hereticks Books; and his own opinion largely deliver'd in juſtification of ſuch puniſhment towards Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104650:28"/>And though <hi>Guiliclmus Pariſienſis</hi> were a Man of that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and gravity in other points,
<note place="margin">Guilielmus Fariſienſis, <hi>De Fide, cap.</hi> 2.</note> herein he ſeems to be moſt ſevere; ſaying, <hi>Quicquid contra veram credulitatem eſt, error eſt. Conſequens igitur eſt, omnem credulitatem quae c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmuni fidei contradicit, errorem eſſe impietatis; &amp; ideo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adio &amp; igne exterminandam.</hi> i. e. <q>What ever is againſt true Faith, is an error. From whence it follows, That all belief which is againſt the common Faith, is an impious error,</q>
                  <note place="margin">Conſideres de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiam Romanam, &amp;c. Epiſcop. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſ. ad Wad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Epist. De Regula.</note> and to be driven out by fire and ſword. So that true is that of <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> to <hi>Wadding</hi> the Jeſuit, whom he adviſes to conſider it; The <hi>Roman</hi> Church holds this for an undoubted Axiome accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his confeſſion, and particularly <hi>Roſweden</hi> in his late Treatiſe of the evil Faith of <hi>Capellus,</hi> that Hereticks are to be put to death, their Books to be burnt, and their Faith to be kept under by eternal ſilence.</p>
               <p>But this ſhort taſt of a plentiful table of ſuch ſtuffe as this, may ſuffice, as to the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> opinion, which their practiſes have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundantly confirmed; of which to ſpeak a little, as it will not be impertinent, ſo to ſpeak much altogether ſuperfluous; the whole being but too apparent.</p>
               <p>And here we may begin with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Inquiſition conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ſo much injuſtice and cruelty as ſcarce can be matched any where. It began, (ſaith <hi>Pedro Paolo</hi>) after the year One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,
<note place="margin">Pedro Paolo, <hi>Histor. Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. pag.</hi> 6.</note> two hundred; the principal Inquiſitors being the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who ſprang up about that time. And about the year of Grace, One thouſand, two hundred, forty four, <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second, Emperor, publiſhed four Edicts at <hi>Padoa,</hi> in favour of the Inquiſitors; whereby, obſtinate Hereticks were to be caſt into the Fire; and, ſuch as repented, were yet to be kept in Priſon perpetually. And this Inquiſition in tract of time hath acquired ſo much ſtrength and ſury, that Princes themſelves have been ſubject to it, and oppreſſed by it, as lamentably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the ſad inſtance of <hi>Charles</hi> Prince and Heir of <hi>Spain,</hi> who upon ſuſpicion only, that he favoured Hereticks, falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Paws of theſe mercileſs Lions, was put to death againſt his Father <hi>Philip's</hi> will,
<note place="margin">Joac. Urſin. <hi>Praefat. ad lib. Reginal.</hi> Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin <hi>de Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioue.</hi>
                  </note> and endeavour to the contrary; as <hi>Joachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> witneſſeth. Yet I know there goes a tradition that his own Father cauſed his death, upon ſuch a ſuſpicion: which, if ſo, the matter is but little mended as to the extream rigor uſed by the Inquiſitors, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Zealots againſt Hereticks.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104650:28"/>Which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> (that Butcher of Chriſtians) further demonſtrated in his Generalſhip over the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> ſo that he gloried at his Table, that, for the extirpating of Hereſie, in the ſpace of ſix years only, he had cauſed to be grievouſly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and put to death about Eighteen thouſand,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>Meteranus <hi>Histor Belgic. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 127. Bellarm. <hi>lib</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>De Lai cis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Baronius: <hi>An.</hi> 1199. numb. 33.</p>
                     <p>Guilielmus Armon. <hi>De re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hilip. gest. apud Bzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> beſides ſuch as he had deſtroyed in the War out of hatred, by private mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders alſo, as <hi>Metaranus</hi> writeth. And long before this, In the days of <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, were burnt of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> a Hundred and eighty at one time, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> teſtifieth, and juſtifieth too: But <hi>Baronius</hi> out-vies him: for he ſaith, that in one day in the year One thouſand, one hundred, eighty three, in the City of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> alone, Seven thouſand of them were ſlain. But anothers report much more ſurpaſſes his, affirming that in the year One thouſand, two hundred and nine, in the ſame City were ſlain Sixty thouſand <hi>Albigenſes.</hi> In the ſame year, in the Village <hi>Minerva</hi> an hundred and eighty were burnt alive. In the year One thouſand, two hundred, and a eleven, Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred were burnt at <hi>Pulchra Vallis.</hi> Again,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>See Bzovius, Matth. Paris, <hi>and quoted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y Doctor</hi> Cracken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorp. <hi>Defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Eccleſ. Angl. Cont. Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſ. cap.</hi> 18. Sleiden <hi>Com. lib</hi> 6</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Meminimus loco vicino Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſileae crematum eſſe quendam propter eſum carnium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Melancthon <hi>Epistola ad</hi> Marchiacas <hi>Eccleſias Cauſſ.</hi> 23. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>cap. Excomm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> Summar. <hi>of Religion, p.</hi> 31.</p>
                  </note> in the ſame year in <hi>Lavarum,</hi> Eighty were put upon Gibbets. In the ſame year Eighty of the Nobles were beheaded; neither did they ſpare the Women. Again, in the year One thouſand, two hundred, and thirteen at <hi>Mirellum</hi> many were cut off by the Sword, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in the River, twenty (<hi>Prateolus</hi> ſaith, Seventy) thouſand were ſlain. In the year One thouſand, two hundred, and ninteen, at <hi>Miromanda</hi> were ſlain 5000. In the year 1236. about fifty were burnt or buried alive. And in the year One thouſand, two hundred, forty two, in a ſmall Village in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſs of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> about Two hundred were burned. By all which we ſee clearly what Execution the Inquiſition did, newly then erected. <hi>Sleiden</hi> tells us further of one who was burnt, becauſe he could not approve of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Rites. And <hi>Melancthon</hi> of another, who was burnt in a place not far from <hi>Baſile,</hi> becauſe he did eat Fleſh. All which agrees perfectly with the definition of Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ban,</hi> who ſaith, <q>We do not judg them to be Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, who, out of zeal to Catholick Church, ſhall kill ſome Excommunicate perſons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And in <hi>France</hi> Twenty thouſand men were ſlain in, and about <hi>Paris,</hi> upon the Licence given, by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> to root
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104650:29"/>out the <hi>Evangelicks,</hi> as <hi>Sleiden</hi> reports to us. To this, if we add the inhuman as well as unchriſtian Fact of <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. of <hi>France,</hi> by whoſe Connivence and Concurrence, if not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſo many thouſands of <hi>Hugonots</hi> were Maſſacr'd for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther real Reaſons, but becauſe they were of The Religion; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever bluſhing at the Immanity of the Fact, a pitiful groundleſs tale was told concerning Plots ſhould nave been laid by them; we need proceed no further: For ſuch an intolerable and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous piece of Barbarity it was, that our Adverſaries, and their Friends that committed the ſame, have nothing more, or better, to anſwer for it; but that we are too prone to remember it: and they too prone to commit ſuch Butcheries and Inhumanities againſt them, that differ from them in Religion, and are too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to learn of them.</p>
               <p>Not long after the Firſt Light of Reformation in <hi>Spain,</hi> were eſtimated about 2000 of that Profeſſion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sr.</hi> Edwin Sandes.</note> and were it not, (ſaith a diligent Obſerver of Men and Countries) for the Inquiſition, all the Country would ſoon be overſpread with them of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion. In <hi>Sevil</hi> alone were thought to be 12000, who all by the violence and vigilance of the Inquiſition, have been ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and brought to nothing. Let not <hi>Papiſts</hi> therefore won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and brag both, of their plentiful Harveſt they have of late days reaped of Proſelytes, by putting their Sickle into our Corn, for, were it ſo, that ſuch remiſſion of Laws, ſuch an indifferency were cheriſhed and countenanced in Perſons, ſuch a permiſſion and favour to Seducers were granted, as is apparent hath been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to our Adverſaries, it would appear in a ſhort time in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> what a great difference there would be in the ſucceſs, to the advantage of our Religion.</p>
               <p>And can any doubt be made, what favor or Toleration we are to expect from <hi>Papiſts</hi> here, in this Nation; were we in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their hands, as they either are, or might be in ours, how they would diſpoſe of us; when it is ſo unanſwerably evident how it tolerably they have Perſecuted our Religion already in <hi>England:</hi> ſo that, as one obſerves, in two of the ſix years Raign of <hi>Queen Mary</hi> only,
<note place="margin">Epistola An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Ridleium De Coena Domini.</note> diverſe Teſtimonies and Letters teſtifie no fewer than 800 perſons were put to moſt cruel deaths in <hi>England,</hi> for their Religion only. And our <hi>Acts and Monuments,</hi> of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104650:29"/>their Bloody minds and hands are ſuch laſting evidences againſt them, that they have no better way to ſave their reputation, but by ſcoffs, and merrie Flouts, which with ſuch as are ambitious to be counted Witts, rather than Religious, is of greateſt Force. And that Lack-manners and honeſty <hi>Parſons</hi> ſhall be heard upon his ſcurrilous humour, rather than he, whoſe Shoes he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to carry; as to Learning, Fidelity, or Piety. Tis not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied what is moſt colourably objected, that Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> might ſet ſuch down for Martyr'd Perſons who ſuffered not. But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that he, following the Decrees and Sentence of Death publickly extant againſt ſuch perſons, together, with the time and place determined for that end, might authentickly deliver that for done (though peradventure ſuch things might interpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lips and the Cup, which might alter Sentence given) which particularly, and preciſely to find out through all <hi>England,</hi> was very hard.</p>
               <p>And to write a Hiſtory, or rather a Tragedy of what was Acted by Rebellions, Treaſons, and Conſpiracies in King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixths, Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> his daies only, for their Religion, were to ſpeak truths moſt pertinent to our ſubject, but ſhameful to ſuch, as are of that Communion, and plead for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. How do we wiſh for no other teſtimonie, than that of their own Conſciences; how incompatible with Civil Unity and Peace this Deſign is? how certainly it would turn, and is by them intended for our Ruine and Deſtruction, as well as their own ſafety? and we needed not ſuch, and ſo many ſad and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Inſtances of their Irreconcilableneſs to, and Inconſiſtency with us, in any co-ordination or equality of Priviledges? How do we wiſh that men would be ſo fair, as to ſtand to their own Hands of outward Practices, and then needed there no curious Inquiries into mens judgments, or reſolutions: But when mens Cauſe and Hearts ſo far fail them, that they dare ſtand to the Tryal of neither of theſe, but will have judgment paſs on them by the future, which is inviſible, and impoſſible to be known but by what is paſt; and when neither their Pens, nor their Swords ſhall conclude, but a ſorry word or two in their ſtraits, ſhall be taken for ſufficient proof of Natures and Wills: then doth there remain nothing for us, to betake our ſelves to, but our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104650:30"/>Prayers; and them, not ſo much that God would keep us in our Religion, but Wits.</p>
               <p>Divers are their Papers and Pamphlets, whereby they would amuſe ſuch as underſtand or regard nothing, with the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of their Religion, and the merits of their Perſons; but both the one and the other have been, with all ocular Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, convicted of the contrary by ſober and plain replies made unto them. They Maſcarate themſelves moſt frequently under the plauſible and taking Appellations of Old Cavaliers, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo diſparaged the King and Churches party, they exſpatiate with ſtrange levity and vain glory in the common place of Self-admiration, and higheſt commendations:
<note place="margin">Letter of an Old Cavalier in <hi>Yorkshire</hi> to one in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> What Men of parts, and power, and ingenuity, and fortitude of mind, in bearing Perſecutions, which have been hitherto nothing but acts of Grace and favour. But they tell us not how they laugh in their ſleeves at all Proclamations and Laws for their reſtraint, and baniſhment of their Seminaries, and Incendiaries, as being ſecure in the midſt of ſuch inſignificant thunders, and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in the midſt of their pretended fears. And from truth and ſobriety of language are they degenerated in their writings into ſuch frivolous, fallacious, and meer childiſh humours of moving compaſſion, where reaſon cannot be ſhaken, that a Man of any inſight in the courſe and cauſes of things cannot but deſpiſe their empty and groundleſs Apologies. I ſhall touch but two of their more common pleas, and places for themſelves, and ſo leave them. The one is, That <hi>Papiſts</hi> are tolerated in divers Parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> in <hi>Holland, Switzerland,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and I know not where elſe: as if that were all true which they affirm in this particular; or, as if ſo much as is true were any whit to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe: For, neither in the Free Cities in <hi>Germany,</hi> or certain Countries (as they would ſuggeſt and perſwade againſt the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledg of the wiſeſt) are either Papiſts tolerated in Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Countries, or Proteſtants in Popiſh. But in the firſt troubles and diſſentions (even to civil diſcords and armings on both ſides) an accord was at length made, and compoſition, That ſuch Churches and Places ſhould belong to Papiſts, and ſuch to Proteſtants; ſo that they never had one over another perfect Dominion, either Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, from the ruptures made
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104650:30"/>amongſt them; whence it is evident, that the one beareth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed with the other, but neither gives Toleration to other. And this is the Caſe chiefly of <hi>France:</hi> where, though the true Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of both be of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, yet cannot it be ſaid that he freely gives them Toleration, ſince that was concluded upon when it was not in the King's power to deny, and was ratified in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, which they of the Religion (as they are called) made with their Prince (whether orderly or irregularly is not now under queſtion) upon the mutual pacification; ſo that the Laws of that Nation and the conſtitution thereof do as truly require the inviolable obſervation thereof on one ſide as on the other, and ſecure the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. But our Laws are directly contrary thereunto, and the reaſon hereof is well known to be, the unreaſonableneſs and indomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table malice and miſchief of Papiſts extorting theſe ſevere Edicts.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Holland,</hi> what Toleration have they? Any Legal, or Publick Act of Grace in that behalf, which is pleaded for here? Nothing leſs: but they and their Religion are at the diſpoſal of Military Officers to repreſs, or permit, according as gain ſhall ariſe to them from a Connivance. And let any indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon judg, whether the Caſes be alike: and eſpecially in this, That ſuch as are <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> have expended their lives and treaſures to bring the <hi>State</hi> to that condition it now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys; and ſurely may with good reaſon expect ſome benefit of quiet and eaſe under the ſame: On the other ſide, our <hi>Papiſts</hi> have perpetually machinated, and to their Power executed Plots and practiſes pernicious to our preſent Government both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, and thereby forfeited all Protection of Laws, and common ſufferance.</p>
               <p>And whereas they never ceaſe, as with the ſwell'd cheeks of Fame to ſound out their own praiſes for their late adherence to <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in his Warrs againſt the Rebells (which is their Second main Topick for Indulgences;) How do theſe their Merits melt away, not ſo much before the Sun, as Candle; ſhewing theſe great Flaws in their pretences, and Inſolidities? Firſt, put Caſe that they had done ſuch ſingular and ſignal ſervice (though I think that the Kings Cauſe was never, in the groſs, advanced by the moſt valiant common Drunkard, or noted <hi>Papiſt,</hi> through the Scandal given to them of ſober Manners, or Religion) Did
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104650:31"/>they riſe in their Allegiance above the duty of Subjects? Again, Were they all on that ſide? Were they all of that mind? Did none of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faction, act to the prejudice of the King? How apparent is it, what a mixture of <hi>Papiſts</hi> heads there was, in the laying the Deſign of the Rebellion, as well in <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Ireland?</hi> and how Prieſts of all ſorts mingled themſelves, diſguiſed in the Parliaments Army, to widen and inflame Differences? There are Treatiſes extant ſhewing this, which though peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may have over acted their part, yet ſo much of reality do they contain,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Williams</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Oſſory</hi> Diſcovery of Myſteries. <hi>pag.</hi> 52.</note> which notably may allay the braggs of unſpotted fidelity to their King and Countrey. Biſhop <hi>Williams,</hi> in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe be wrote in the heat, and height of Rebellion, tells us upon his own knowledg, that of Fifty, or Sixty Soldiers that billetted in <hi>Adthorp,</hi> there was no leſs than three or four <hi>Papiſts</hi> of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Army. Add hereunto the idle, as well as treacherous Piece of Mr. <hi>White, Of Government,</hi> whereby he aſſerted the Right of Rule, belonging only to the Line of our Kings, to him that villanouſly Uſurped it, or any one elſe that could get it; and their faithfulneſs ſhrinks into a leſs compaſs. Beſides, be it true, that they were ſo generally Couragious, and Faithful to their King, as is talk'd of; Could no ſufficient agnition, or remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be thought of, but ſuch as turned to the extream dammage of ſuch, as were no leſs Faithful and Loyal, than were they? Or, did they not only purchaſe glory and benefit to themſelves, but miſery and undoing to others, by their Merits? They were not (it may be as truly, as boldly ſaid) above the Twentieth Part of the Kings Forces. Whence comes it then, that they make more noiſe than all others? From their generous minds which they boaſt of? And muſt the Generality of the Nation be certainly undon that they may receive their juſt reward? But that the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt in ſhort time loſe its Religion, and Sacrifice it to theirs, is moſt apparent, out of what hath been ſhewed of their Tenets, and Facts, who never reſt till they are chief; and being chief, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuffer men of another Perſwaſion to live, ſo much as baſely under them. But then, muſt they not be requited and gratified for their Acts? Surely, their reward hath followed them, in that their Perſons and Eſtates have been Reſcued out of the hands of their, and our Enemies, by the favourable Influence of the Kings
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104650:31"/>Government; and more they cannot modeſtly contend for. Or, if we ſhould grant a Proportion greater to them, than any of the Kings Subjects elſe, might it not ſuffice that they have perſonal Priviledges of Preferment, Dignities, or Liberty to themſelves; but muſt their Acts ſo far preponderate all of another Religion in the ſame ſervice with them, that they ought to tranſmit to Poſterity ſuch rewards; and theſe immunities from Laws muſt they for their ſakes be granted to all as are nothing akin to them but by Religion? But conſider we laſtly, with what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and motives, their Loyalties were qualified: and we may eaſily diſcern that Self-preſervation might be as ſtrong an argument, as was their famed Loyalty. For they ſaw plainly the Rebel-Houſes aimed at their Ruine, and ſeized their Eſtates. Had they any more profitable way then left them, or probable, to oppoſe their Enemies, than by giving Aſſiſtance to the King? And when their own Intereſt might ſuffice to joyn with him, as is frequent for neighbours to aſſiſt their weaker Enemies, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a more potent and dangerous Adverſary; muſt this be cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, as ſuch incomparable good Service, as can never, nor any other way, be recompenced but by opening a door to our own Perdition? When they ſo cheerfully, and cleerly eſpouſe the Cauſe of King and Country againſt their Religious Intereſt, (as hitherto they have only joyntly with it) it will be much more ſeaſonable and proper to demand ſuch Remunerations (though not ſo great) as now they expect. But to ſtretch to ſuch length, breadth, and height their late Actions by Amplifications and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums, as if they could as eaſily merit Earth, as Heaven, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcarce their duty; and to faign themſelves even half mad with admiration, and aſtoniſhment, that any of the Friends to the King, ſhould yet ſuſpect them of Diſloyalty, is but to follow the humor of their Religion, which teaches, Becauſe their Church hath not erred at ſometimes, therefore at no time muſt it be thought for to Erre. Which yet, as unreaſonable as to all the World it appears, we will engage to comply with them in, when they ſhall be able to give but the tithe of Inſtances for their peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs and loyalty, as we ſhall for their Seditions, Treaſons, Rebellions, and Conſpiracies againſt all Government not hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Profeſſion. In a word, never let their unparallel'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104650:32"/>confidence in juſtification of themſelves as to Obedience and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty prevaile over them, to imagine we will deny our Senſes and Experience, and all Record, and Hiſtories to the contrary: For, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e there no more ingenious way to put theſe things out of doubt, we would readily pawn our Heads againſt their Beards, and our Lives againſt their meaneſt Limbs, that ſo far as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and actions paſt can give any proof of future diſpoſitions, and motions, (I do not ſay a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> but) <hi>Popery</hi> cannot conſiſt with the Peace of this Nation or Church, as now eſtabliſhed, we will undertake to Demonſtrate; when ever they ſhall be ſo bold as to tempt us to put them to ſo much juſt and neceſſary ſhame. And in truth, this has been ſo far and fully done, and that lately by others, that were, it my preſent deſign (as it is not) to paint them out in their Poſtures, and Colours, the labour would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary: This therefore will I leave for them to be ſtill aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, and me to prove; That a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as a <hi>Papiſt</hi> and following the moſt received and current Doctrine taught by that Church, (ſome I eaſily grant, as in all other points, may vary ſomewhat, but they are but few, and contemptible with them,) and put in practiſe can never be a Loyal Subject, under any Prince not of the <hi>Romiſh-Church,</hi> any longer than neceſſity humbles him, and deſpair of proſperous ſucceſs keeps him tame. Let us therefore hear what the other Extream, the <hi>Puritan,</hi> hath to plead for, or rather againſt, himſelf; and whether he be a Child of better hopes, who gives us the very ſame promiſes with the other, and himſelf the ſame praiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Opinions and Practice of</hi> Puritans, <hi>directly oppoſite to that kind of Liberty of Conſcience they argue for, and at preſent deſire.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT hath been obſerved by ſome, that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> had their Original at the ſame time, with the difference of one year only. For the <hi>Puritans</hi> began to ſhew their Head in the year 1536; and the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> were admitted at <hi>Rome</hi> in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104650:32"/>year 1537.
<note place="margin">Sanderus <hi>De Haereſih. p.</hi> 221. Genebrardus. <hi>Chronol. Anno</hi> 1566.</note> But <hi>Sanders</hi> and <hi>Genebrard</hi> affirm they ſprang up in the year 1566. And I have heard the Providence of God towards the Church admired and magnified amongſt Foreign Papiſts, who at the ſame time that the Presbyterians aroſe, ſtirred up the Jeſuites to oppoſe and countermine them. And I find it one of the beſt popular arguments in the mouths, and lately in the writings, of Presbyterians, That they ought to be tolerated, and not only ſo but cheriſhed in this Church, for their ſingular enmity and oppoſition to Popery; which, when they are once put down, they give out muſt needs enter in. For thus ſpeaks one of no ſmall account with them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John orbets</hi> Intereſt of England, <hi>pag.</hi> 46.</note> 
                  <hi>And verily if there were a deſign to reconcile</hi> England <hi>to</hi> Rome, <hi>let all means be uſed totally to quaſh the Puritans or Presbyterians; but if</hi> England <hi>will keep her ſelf pure from</hi> Romiſh <hi>abominations, let her be a kind Mother to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe her Children; for this Intereſt is one chief ſtrength of the Reformed Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Thus he.</p>
               <p>An argument, as current as it is, this is, conſiſting equally of Folly and Knavery, as will thus appear. Firſt, becauſe we having found by direful experience that the Presbyterians, as well as the Papiſts, have not only contrived and conſpired againſt our Churches welfare, but have actually moſt ſcandalouſly and cruelly endeavoured the utter overthrow of the ſame, and ſtill ſtick firmly to the ſame Principles, which inſtigated them to ſuch unnatural and unjuſt practiſes; may not their argument (as indeed it hath been) be turned thus againſt them for the Papiſts? Verily if there be a deſign to become Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, then let the Papiſts be totally quaſhed; but if <hi>England</hi> will keep her ſelf pure from the Dominations of <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presbytery, then let her be kind to the Papiſts, who have done as much againſt them as they have againſt the Papiſts; thus does the extream vanity of their argument appear; the only courſe to preſerve our ſelves in peace and unity being to ſerve them both alike. Again, were it ſo that by accident (for it cannot be ſaid out of deſign to the good of our Church) either of them might contribute ſomewhat to the good of the Church as now eſtabliſhed, the rule which <hi>Seneca</hi> gives us in ſuch caſes is not to be neglected,
<note place="margin">Seneca <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ideò vitia recipienda ſurt quia aliquando al quid boni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffecerunt,</hi> 
                  <q>Evils are not to be admitted, becauſe at certain times they have had ſome good effect.</q> So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought we to run to Popery for fear of Presbytery, nor run to Presbytery, for fear of Popery. But the way of arguing is likewiſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104650:33"/>very knaviſh, in that by implication, a wicked ſlander is caſt upon our Church, that it muſt needs favour Popery, if Puritaniſm be wholly rejected; But if we deny them ſuch prevaricating Reaſonings, we cut them out of all their prime confidences, and take away their moſt principal and ſucceſsful Weapons. Therefore, leaving this, let us come nearer to their teſtimonies againſt themſelves. In which, becauſe they pretend great reverence to Foreign Divines of the Reformation, it will not be much out of the way to ſet down one or two of their Authorities againſt them.</p>
               <p>It is well known that <hi>Beza</hi> hath written a Tractate on purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Beza <hi>de Hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratu puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endis.</hi>
                  </note> That Magiſtrates may, and ought to puniſh Hereticks, which they of his ſide, who doubt of this point, may turn to, and be convinced. I ſhall cite this only paſſage out of him, and ſo leave him. <hi>Cedò igitur Chriſtus quo jure flagella his corripuit? Quo jure Petrus Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam &amp; Sapphiram occidit? Quo jure Paulus Elymam excoecavit? Num Eccleſiaſtici Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rii? Minimè profectò. &amp;c.</hi> [you that hold that the Magiſtrate ought not to puniſh Hereticks] Tell me I pray, By what authority did Chriſt twice take a whip up? By what authority did <hi>Peter</hi> put to death <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira?</hi> By what authority did <hi>Paul</hi> put out the eyes of <hi>Elymas?</hi> What, by the Eccleſiaſtical Miniſtry? Nothing leſs truly, unleſs thou wilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Juriſdictions. Therefore was it done by the authority of the Civil Magiſtrate: For, there is no third way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> writeth not only againſt profeſſed Hereticks, but ſuch as call themſelves tender-conſcienc'd men too, allowing them toleration no longer than they may receive ſufficient inſtruction; and addeth,
<note place="margin">Petrus Martyr <hi>Loc. Com. Claſ.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>numb.</hi> 32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Imò neque in ipſis mediis rebus Infirmis est aſſentiendum, niſi tantiſper dum melius ac per fectiùs doceantur. Ac cum rem, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Yea, neither in things indifferent are we to yield to the weak, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for a while, until they may be better and more fully inſtructed: But ſo ſoon as they have underſtood the matter, and yet are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, their weakneſs is not to be cheriſhed. Beſides, ſo much ought not to be attributed unto ſuch, as that by our example we ſhould hurt others, and more of the members of Chriſt.</q> Thus <hi>Martyr.</hi> And it is to us plain (however they muſt and may be of another opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) that by giving way to them that thus pretend tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, we ſhould offend Conſciences a great deal better ſetled,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104650:33"/>and more to be regarded and valued than theirs, which (as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from cruel havock they have made in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, aſſures us) ſtrain at a guat and ſwallow a Camel.</p>
               <p>And what other courſe took the <hi>Contra-remonſtrants</hi> againſt their Brethren in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> after the Council of <hi>Dort,</hi> but this; when they refuſed to ſubmit to the ſentence then given?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act. Synodal. pag.</hi> 324.</note> They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That every one ſhould be deprived of all, as well Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical as. Scholaſtical Offices, who refuſed to ſubmit punctually to the Acts of the Synod; and,
<note place="margin">Synodal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrat. in Praefat.</note> that no man ſhould be admitted to the Miniſtry for the time to come, who refuſed to ſubſcribe to the Doctrine there declared, and preach according unto the ſame: And in purſuance of that final determination, no fewer than two hundred of the Oppoſite Party, who could not conform to the Acts thereof, were forthwith baniſhed the Country; a Proclamation following them from the Magiſtrate, That no Man ſhould afford them any help or maintenance. Does not this match for a hair the extreameſt perſecution can at preſent be objected to the Church againſt Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans? Or rather doth it not exceed it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bullinger</hi> telleth us with full approbation and commendation,
<note place="margin">Bullingerus <hi>Epist ad</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum <hi>Epist.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>3 <hi>inter</hi> Cal. vini <hi>Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>olas.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dudum D. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus Regius una cum om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibus Luneburgenſibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Miniſtris, edito etiam libro Germanico jure divino &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano coerceri Haereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, tum etiam ju e civil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; ſi non deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant impia, &amp;c.</hi> i. e. <q>Maſter <hi>Urbanus Regius,</hi> together with all the Miniſters of <hi>Luneberg</hi> hath lately publiſhed a Book in the <hi>German</hi> tongue, whereby he ſheweth that by the Law of God and Man, and Civil Law too, Hereticks ought to be reſtrained, if they ceaſe not to ſcatter wicked Doctrines, or have ſcatter'd blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</q> And in the ſame Epiſtle he telleth us, Not long ſince <hi>Titian,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Anabaptiſt, an <hi>Hebionite,</hi> and <hi>Helvidian</hi> was caſt into priſon by the three Confederate Countries of <hi>Rhetia,</hi> and had <q>been burnt, had he not made a Recantation; and yet, notwithſtanding that, was whipt by the Court.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And what <hi>Calvin's</hi> opinion was in this point we needed not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire further than we are taught from his Fact, principally in cauſing <hi>Servetus</hi> to be burnt at <hi>Geneva.</hi> But his Inſtitutions and Epiſtles, where he is much diſpleaſed with good <hi>Melancthon</hi> for ſtraitning the breaches, and qualifying the diſtempers of both ſides; and on the other ſide, his Book againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> do clearly ſhew and prove unto us.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104650:34"/>
               <p>But whoever pleaſeth to ſatisfie himſelf more fully and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning the opinions of Foreign Divines in the caſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience about the granting liberty to ſcrupulous perſons in matters of Indifferency, may conſult <hi>Monſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eur Durels</hi> diligent Collections of ſeveral of them, negatively concluding againſt Liberty in indifferent things, to any or many ſingle perſons, contrary to the conſtitutions of a Church: And in truth, they that contend for the ſame cannot ſhew a Church upon earth that indulges ſo far. So equal and ingenuous are they to tug ſo undeniably for it of us.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Chriſtian O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience from, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 33.</note> But I now draw home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, where I may be the more brief, becauſe Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> hath to any reaſonable mans hand, already proved this Theſis, That Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates may compell their Subjects againſt their pretended conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to Eccleſiaſtical Orders.</p>
               <p>Who of them can refuſe Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> the Aurhors of the Admonition compiled in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days, and many Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to the Parliaments in thoſe days? do not they all run in one ſtrain of aboliſhing utterly the eſtabliſhed Government? and <hi>Cartwright</hi> in particular excepting againſt the Common Prayer for permitting the people to depart at the time of Communion; ſaith, <q>It ought to provide that all thoſe who would withdraw themſelves,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Cartwright</hi> Reply to <hi>Whitgiſt. pag.</hi> 117.</note> ſhould be by Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline at all times, and now alſo under a Godly, &amp;c. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> by Civil puniſhment brought to communicate with their Brethren. And this is the Law of God, and this is now, and hath been, the practiſe of the Churches Reformed, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And I hope they take not Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> to be any of their Enemies, though I think he had too much Learning and Honeſty to be a Fautor of ſuch deſignes and practiſes as are now on Foot: He, in a certain place,
<note place="margin">Perkins <hi>on Galat.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 201, &amp; 202. <hi>vide.</hi>
                  </note> writes thus, <q>In perſecution of the Church by <hi>Paul,</hi> two points are to be conſidered, The manner or meaſure, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment; the manner is, That he perſecuted the Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, or above meaſure. That which <hi>Paul</hi> did in his Religion we muſt do in ours.</q> His meaning plainly is, That as <hi>Paul</hi> in a falſe Religion and Zeal did perſecute the true, ſo we in the true (and ſurely every man ſuppoſes himſelf of the true Religion) ought to perſecute the falſe. And afterward he hath theſe words, <q>The Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of two Religions in one Kingdom is the overthrow of Peace.</q>
                  <note place="margin">Id. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.15.</note> And in another place of the ſame Comment upon the <hi>Galatians,</hi> he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104650:34"/>hath theſe words, <q>For this cauſe, the <hi>Jewes</hi> had but one Temple,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Id. Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.</hi> 3.23 <hi>pag.</hi> 289.</note> one Mercy-ſeat, one High-Prieſt, &amp;c. Hence it follows, that in all Godly Chriſtian Commonwealths where true Religion is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, there may be no Toleration of any other Religion. For, that which is the end of Gods Laws, muſt likewiſe be the end of all good Laws, in all Commonwealths and Kingdoms, namely to ſhut up the people into the unity of one Faith.</q> Thus far Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</hi> And before all theſe he gives a notable reaſon for Conſtraint. <q>For, ſaith he, The multitude of people amongſt us are like Wax,
<note place="margin">Id. <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.6, 7.</note> and are fit to take the ſtamp and impreſſion of any Religion; and it is the Law of the Land, that makes moſt receive the Goſpel, and not Conſcience.</q> And as he brings a reaſon here for conſtraint, ſo doth he elſe where remove an Objection commonly brought againſt it; which is this, <q>It may be ſaid,
<note place="margin">Id. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.15.</note> that Faith and Conſcience are free. I anſwer (ſaith he) though Faith in the heart, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be free in reſpect of mans authority, yet is not the publiſhing of Faith and Profeſſion of Conſcience free in like ſort, but it ſtands ſubject to the power of the Magiſtrate.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But it is time now to deſcend yet lower to the Doctrine of ſuch who were of the ſame Confederacy with the preſent ſuers for liberty. In the year of our Lord 1641. Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> preached his famous piece on <hi>Numbers</hi> 23.5. of, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> his Sermon before the Houſe, 1641.</note> which is nothing leſs than Toleration of tender Conſciences (if it be lawful to ſuppoſe any conſcience can be tender which differs from them) but drives on with a fury them who were not backward to oppreſs men in their Conſciences and Religion. Amongſt other things this he leaves with his Auditors, coming to Application, that being obliged to curſe their Adverſaries, this Curſing conſiſted in two things, <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere Verbo,</hi> and <hi>Malefacere Re.</hi> They were to curſe or ſpeak evil of them in Word. And they were to do them miſchief in Deed.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Faircloth,</hi> preaching in the ſame year againſt <hi>Achans</hi> Villany,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sam. Faircloth</hi> Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Apr.</hi> 4. 1641.</note> and <hi>Joſuah</hi>'s zeal againſt him, declares much againſt the <hi>Achans</hi> that hindered the intended Reformation, and the toleration of the Church-party, yea, againſt Procraſtination of Severities againſt them; <hi>pag.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. And <hi>pag.</hi> 40, 41. he anſwereth the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of delay taken from <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> with Application, 1. of Praiſe. 2. of Prayer. Then comes he to Motives:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 44, 45.</note> It is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104650:35"/>God's will,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 49.</note> you make ſpeed. 2. <hi>Achaus</hi> make ſpeed to do hurt. 3. Delay hinders the joy and jubilee of the Church. 4. Ye ſhall bring bleſſings to your ſelves.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 50, 51.</note> 5. Juſtice executed on them, is the only end of all your Prayers. Thus he. Now if they by an uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority acting, taught ſuch zeal againſt their Superiors; can they hold it unreaſonable that Legal authority ſhould proceed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own Maxims? But I ſhall not need to repeat innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable inſtances which might be given of their impatience at the name of Toleration or Moderation, which they were wont to brand with the note of Deteſtable Neutrality. What was that language or deſign which <hi>Cartwright</hi> of old taught our late ſticklers, but a thorow Reformation?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cartwright</hi> Preface to his Reply.</note> and how did he, and they after him, propound the examples of <hi>Ezechiah, Joſiah,</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at,</hi> for that they made whole and thorow. <hi>Reformation, &amp;c.</hi> and is there any amongſt them, or us, ſo ignorant that knows not what they meant by thorow-Reformation? and that in truth, as their Covenants and Actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, was nothing elſe but the utter exſtirpation of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Government and ſubverſion of the Church then, and ſo conſtituted: But peradventure they would now for peace ſake (and ſo ought we to) divide and ſhare alike. I know this is the tale they have got at their tongues end now a days, whereby they procure the eſteem by ſome, of Moderate Men. But is this with any ſerious or diſcerning man a tolerable argument for them, when as never were there any perſons ſo violent, rank, or extream in their principles but when they found it not poſſible to obtain what their principles, and deſign impell them to contend for, ſeem at leaſt ſatisfied with ſo much as they can get, though they will no longer reſt ſo than advantage ſhall carry them further. But let us hear what Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> ſpake, when the Faction was low, againſt ſuch a peace as now is preferred to us: And you may not only read the ſame deſign, but words and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments exactly in theſe more modern Reformers, which Mr. <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> had, and the ſame ſpirit acting both him and theſe, <q>Peace (ſaith he) is commended to us with theſe conditions.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cartwright</hi> Preface to his Reply.</note> [If it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, if it lies in us.] Now it is not poſſible it lieth not in us, to conceal the truth; we can do nothing againſt it, but for it.</q> It is a prophane ſaying of a prophane man. That <hi>an unjuſt peace</hi> in better <hi>than a juſt War?</hi> Who ſees not from hence moſt plainly, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but every thing will ſatisfie theſe men? And do they not hold
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104650:35"/>that an unjuſt peace, whereby they are kept in quiet without their diſcipline? and is not that a juſt War which is made for its ſake? More a great deal (all know) might be added againſt them from their own mouths and hands; he that ſtill doubts may look into that Treatiſe called <hi>Evangelium Armatum;</hi> which, though an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and indeed an abortive piece in compariſon of what was due to ſuch a ſubject, yet doth ſufficiently declare their tempers and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions to be againſt all mediocrity or compounding of Differences. I have not touched any thing therein; nor is that famous Mr. <hi>Love</hi> the Presbyterian <hi>Martyr</hi> there mentioned (as I remember) or at leaſt, not his Ranting and Railings at the attempted or pretended ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation to be made by the Presbyterian Faction at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg,</hi> with the King; nor his Sermon at <hi>Windſor,</hi> where, in the flame of his zeal for the Cauſe, he exhorted the people to ſell their Bibles, and buy Muskets to fight againſt the King, and being (as he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) lead to it by his Text, ſpake thus, That if God ſhould go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King's Party, He ſhould be the greateſt ſinner upon Earth: which paſſage ſo exorbitant being heard and excepted againſt by one of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he was called to account for ſpeaking ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverently of Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> before the Governour of <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle; but publickly affirming and proving the ſame to be as he reported, by appeal to many Auditors of his, then preſent, who could not deny they heard the words; he was rebuked for not making the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of what godly men taught. The ſame Mr. <hi>Love</hi> (ſo paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and charitable a ſpirit are they acted by) mounting the Scaffold at the Execution of the moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> put to death to ſatiate the <hi>Scots</hi> appetite, and ſuch as ſymbolize with them, after Prelatical blood, with greateſt exſultation ſpringing at the ſight, utter'd theſe words, Art thou come Little <hi>Will?</hi> I am glad to ſee thee here, and hope to ſee the reſt of the Biſhops here e're long: And that moſt innocent blood being ſhed on the Stage at his beheading, he took out his Handkerchief and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ained it therewith; and the Murther being over he rode with it to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg,</hi> and drawing it forth in the preſence of divers perſons ſpake thus moſt triumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Here is the blood of that proud Prelate; I hope for more of their bloods e're long. Which Mr. <hi>A. F.</hi> Commiſſary to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> hearing, ſaid to ſome then preſent, and divers elſewhere afterwards before his death; that he could not believe ſuch a bloody man would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104650:36"/>die in his bed. And ſo by the ſtrange and juſt hand of Providence it came to paſs, himſelf ſuffered in the very ſame manner that he had rejoyced to ſee in others. But yet becauſe he made uſe of the King's name to advance his Presbytery from <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>land</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> this muſt be ſet on the ſcore as an high inſtance to prove, what good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Presbyterians can be, when their Diſcipline requires it.</p>
               <p>But paſſing ſimple authorities and teſtimonies of Puritans againſt themſelves pleading for Toleration; we may come to a further double ſelf-condemnation of them. And to this end I might inſert here what hath been ſo lately reprinted and publiſhed of the Presbyterian Brethren of Sion-Colledg,
<note place="margin">A Letter of the Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Sion-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg</hi> to the Synod of Divines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rinted.</note> or Miniſters of the City of <hi>London,</hi> to their Brethren of the Synod then at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> againſt Toleration of <hi>Independents.</hi> Which is ſo pregnant and cutting a way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them, that I know not what poſſibly can be urged more juſtly and reaſonably by us, or leſs anſwered by them. For, I think they will bluſh (who have not forſworn it) to ſay, we have any grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or better grounds to tolerate them, than they the Independents. For my part, I could never underſtand they had any Authority over theſe, or the ſeparation of Independents from Presbytery was ever any more a Schiſm than the Presbyterians oppoſition to, or ſeparation from, the Independents. For, though both of them (I mean ſome of both Parties) might be ſaid in ſome ſenſe to be of a Church, neither of them were ever a true Church, as bungled and patched together by their novel imaginations. Yet ſuch was the jealouſie and emulation of Presbyterians, that they would be no means have any co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Faction with their own, ſuffered.</p>
               <p>I had once therefore determined, to the end that all the World, and eſpecially themſelves, might ſtand convicted of the unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of their demands and expectations at preſent, to give the ſum of their arguments; but conſidering how ſmall a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe that is, and how lately it is come forth, I ſhall preſume that it is already well known. And I ſhall only give the ſum of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> Reaſons, famous for his Pieces called the <hi>Gangreen,</hi> wherein he argues ſtrenuouſly againſt the Toleration of <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> then,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Edwards</hi> his Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Anno</hi> 1641.</note> and of his own Party now. To prove this then more methodically and ſtrongly, he lays theſe two general grounds againſt Toleration. Firſt, ſays he, Apoſtolical Practice is againſt this. Secondly, It cauſes men to run into the Violation of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104650:36"/>conſtant practiſe and example of the Church, during all the time of the Apoſtles: and puts Churches upon practiſes that are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, and unreaſonable, and prejudicial to the good of Souls: That Government that is not of Divine Inſtitution, is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: But the <hi>Independent</hi> doth ſo, faith Mr. <hi>Edwards;</hi> and we much more juſtly, But the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> doth ſo.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.4.</note> And we prove it by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his words following, <hi>They force men to have Miniſters and Officers without being Ordained, contrary to the practice of the Churches all along the New Teſtament: as</hi> Act. 6. v. 6. Act. 4.23. <hi>No man being Ordained Officer of the Church, without Ordination: Let them produce one Inſtance if they can.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi> Now, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> being dead, I in his ſtead challenge any, yea, all the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to give one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thorow all the Old, or New-Teſtament, or the whole Church of God for 1500 years ſince the Incarnation, that a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Presbyter,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> ever Ordained; or, if by higheſt Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they did attempt ſuch a thing at any time, ſuch Ordination was ever accepted, or held good by the Church. But I deſire they would find ſome better ground to prove this, than the Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Biſhop and <hi>Presbyter</hi> anciently: For Firſt, this is no leſs doubted of, than that they would prove by it. Secondly, If becauſe St. <hi>Hierome</hi> is thought to have been of that Opinion, (as ſome take his words) we ſhould ſuppoſe, and not grant, that they were ſo once, it proves nothing now: when it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they are not ſo, nor have been ſo, for many hundred years. And therefore men and women both, impoſing hands upon their Paſtor among <hi>Independents,</hi> if the Ordination of theſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Ordination may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together be of no account among us.</p>
               <p>After this Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> proceeds to prove particularly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Edwards.</hi> ibid.</note> That Toleration is not to be allowed: And Firſt, from the Vanity and Impertinency of the texts of Scripture brought to prove it. <q>For though (ſaith he) the Scripture ſpeaks much for Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bearing one with another in many things, both in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Opinion and Practiſe, as theſe places tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifie. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1, 2, 3, 5, 13, 14, <hi>v. Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2, 7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 23. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16. Yet, when differences come either to <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and Points to be maintaind by men, ſo as to trouble and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104650:37"/>diſturb the Church, then the Scriptures are expreſs againſt their Toleration and ſufferance, requiring them who have Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to hinder it, as may be ſeen, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Titus.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10.</q> 
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 10, 12. and ſo on. And are not the differences now among us come already to <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> and <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Diviſions</hi> amongſt us? are they then any longer to be Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated? Or were theſe and the following Reaſons, only intended for the uſe of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> but muſt loſe all their vertue and validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when that is the Caſe againſt which they make directly?</p>
               <p>Secondly, he at the ſame time anſwers a Principal argument now in great uſe; and confirms his Theſis thus. <q>The Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deſired will not help to heal the <hi>Schiſms</hi> and Rents of this Church, but will much foment and encreaſe them. For whileſt ſome Congregations, and they accounted of note both for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People, will not ſubmit to the Reformation, and Government ſetled by Law; this will breed in the Peoples minds many thoughts <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> that this Church is not ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to the word of God, and is unlawful, &amp;c. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereof follow.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>This Toleration will not only breed Diviſions and Schiſms diſturbing the Peace of Churches and Towns, by ſetting them who are of different Families, and more remote Relations one againſt another; but it will undoubtedly cauſe much Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, Diſcontents, and Diviſions between the neareſt Relations of Husbands and Wives, Fathers and Children, Brothers and Siſters, Maſters and Servants; the Husband being of one Church, and the Wiſe of another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <q>4. There will be great danger of continual Diviſions, Diſtractions, and Diſputes among us, not only from the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Form of Government and Worſhip in their Churches and ours; but from other Doctrines and Practiſes held by ſome of them for the preſent.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <q>The moſt eminent Miniſters of this Kingdom for grace, parts, and labours, can have little aſſurance of the continuance of their Flocks to them, if ſuch a Toleration be granted; For they will draw away their People and admit them into their Churches, and even gather and encreaſe their Churches out of the labours of the beſt Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104650:37"/>
               <p n="6">6. <q>It will be, undoubtedly, a means and way of their infinite Multiplication and Encreaſe; even to encreaſe them thirty Fold.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <q>The prime and Fundamental Principles of this <hi>Independent</hi> (and likewiſe <hi>Presbyterian</hi>) way, upon which they erect their Church-way, are very prejudicial and dangerous, and unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to this Kingdom.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <q>Theſe <hi>Independents,</hi> (and much more <hi>Presbyterian</hi>) men where they have power, would not give a Toleration for any other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Government, or Churches but in their own way: They would not ſuffer men of other Opinions in Doctrine and Government, to live within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounds of their Patent, though at the fartheſt bounds; but have Baniſhed them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <q>A Toleration may be demanded upon the ſame grounds for all the rigid <hi>Browniſts</hi> of the Kingdom, and for all <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Familiſts,</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who profeſs 'tis Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And thus you have the Heads of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Reaſons in the Words of Mr. <hi>Edwards:</hi> which if they may not be more ſtrongly turned againſt themſelves, now moving for Toleration, I muſt profeſs my ſelf to underſtand neither Them, nor their Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, nor the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue. And if men will ſtill perſiſt in their unſeaſonable, unreaſonable, and unconſcionable demands againſt all theſe ſo irrefragable Arguments to the contrary; we have nothing left but our Prayers, Tears, and Confuſion, which our notorious Flagrant Sins have brought upon us: And if Authority deſerts us with ſuch advantages on our ſides, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on Earth can miniſter greater, nor any ſiqual Judg require better; we ſhall eaſily ſee from whence this Judgment comes, and why, (not for any wrong in this Caſe done to our Antagoniſts) <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe we have ſinned, and are come down wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
               <p>I might here conclude all; but that, as I have diſputed againſt them out of their own mouths and books; ſo I judg it not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to ſhow the inſufficiency of their reaſons from their anſwers, or ſuch as they are not wont to queſtion, unleſs when
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104650:38"/>they are to expreſs. And having by the way anſwered ſome already; one or two, may ſuffice to be here touched.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Certain Exceptions, which may be made by</hi> Puritans <hi>againſt what hath been delivered, anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE have already prevented the vulgar, and general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges, made by ignorant and undiſcerning men againſt the way of our Church, and in behalf of their Diſcipline, taken from the miſ-underſtanding of Tyranny, Extreams, Moderation, and Chriſtian Liberty: with which Notions, Seducers are wont to make a great ſhow amongſt well-affected, but ill-adviſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. We have likewiſe even now anſwered that which they offer to the People plauſibly in moſt of their late books, though here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toforewe could never wring a ſyllable from them to that purpoſe, from the great benefit of the Peace of the Church; out of Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi> And that Objection is likewiſe removed by Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> moſt clearly, which urges us, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is Free and cannot be forced. So that there appears not much to remain behind, alledged by them, deſerving further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Yet two, or three things we ſhall add out of them, to the former; and ſo end.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, I fore ſee it may be Excepted, that our diſcourſe generally runs againſt grievous <hi>Hereticks,</hi> where we ſhew the Judgment and Practiſe of the ancient Church againſt them, which will not hold againſt thoſe of our days and Church, who are no <hi>Hereticks.</hi> To which I thus anſwer:</p>
               <p>Firſt, That according to the ſenſe of the Code, the Laws made againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> do comprehend <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and ſuch as differ from the Church in leſſer and lighter matters. <hi>Haeretice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum autem vocabulo continentur, &amp; latis adverſus eos ſanctionibus ſuccumbere debent, qui vel levi argumento a judicio Catholicae Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis &amp; tramite deetcti fuerint deviare.</hi> i. e. <q>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the name of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104650:38"/>Hereticks, are comprehended, and ought to be puniſhed by the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made aegainſt them,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>all ſuch as are found to ſwerve in a light matter from the judgment, and path of Catholick Religion.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They themſelves, (as appears plainly by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) will no more ſuffer <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> (no not their brethren the <hi>Independents,</hi> whom they dare not call <hi>Here ticks,</hi> and who had deſerved ſo well at their hands, (which as yet they never did at ours) than <hi>Hereticks.</hi> 3ly, The practiſe of the ancient Church as in part we have ſhewed, did aſwaies perſecute <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> as well as <hi>Hereticks.</hi> 4ly, The Pſeas and Excuſe of our Diſſenters are not ſo allowable in the principle point of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> as are moſt <hi>Hereticks.</hi> For, there being two Eſſential parts of <hi>Hereſie</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received, A Formal part, conſiſting in the pravity of the mind, and diſpoſition of the heart, and obſtinacy of the will; And a Material part, conſiſting in the Errour it ſelf maintained: Men of our Age and Countrey, have more of the Formality of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> than they who are direct <hi>Hereticks:</hi> Foraſmuch as an <hi>Heretick</hi> erring in Articles of Faith, may be truly ſaid, and allowed to make a conſcience of what he (though Erroniouſly) believes: for being matters of Faith, they are proper Objects of Conſcience, whoſe Sphere is good, and Evil. But they who do not differ, not diſſent (as they ſay) in Matters of Faith from the Church, but yet keep themſelves at a diſtance from the Authority of the ſame, may indeed (whether we will or no) call their diſſenting by the name of Conſcience; but it is well known in reaſon, or propriety of ſpeech, it cannot be ſo termed; when there not ſo much as appears Good, or Evil, in the thing it ſelf: And therefore it muſt of neceſſity be Reſolution not to agree or yield, and that is nothing elſe but obſtmacy, as their own juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations do imply, when, being demanded, why they cannot in Conſcience comply? They (to my knowledge) anſwer, They cannot do it. Fifthly, As Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſaid againſt the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> we may ſay againſt the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> viz. That we know not the bottom of their Reformation, nor where it will end, nor what it doth hold, notwithſtanding their publiſhed Confeſſions, and Catechiſms Larger, or Leſſer; there being infinite Points, which, like obſtructions to a man travailing by Mapps when they ſhall come to put in practice, will ariſe unexpectedly. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> whom they follow as their Modern Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104650:39"/>tells us in their ſtead,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cartwright</hi>'s Reply to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> pag. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Cortain of the things we ſtand upon are ſuch, that if every hair of our head were a life, we ought to afford them for the defence of them.</hi> Again, in the ſame Treatiſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> for diſtinguiſhing between matters of Faith and neceſſary to Salvation;
<note place="margin">Id. pag. 14. And Reply to the Anſwer, pag. 1.</note> and Ceremonies Orders and Diſcipline of the Church; as though (ſaith he) matters of Diſcipline and kind of Government were not matters neceſſary to Salvation and of Faith. Are theſe men underſtood, or to be truſted, when they ſay, they demand only ſuch things as we may eaſily grant? Will they lay down their lives for them?</p>
               <p>Secondly, They profeſs that they are ready to come up to us, if we would grant certain light matters.</p>
               <p>But with what truth and ſincerity let their Actions all along ſpeak, which aimed at nothing leſs than the ruin and abſolute diſſolution of our Church. And let <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> in the next place tell us in theſe words,
<note place="margin">Id. Reply pag. 102.</note> 
                  <hi>Indeed it were more ſafe for us to conform our indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rent Ceremonies to the Turks which are far off, than to the Papists which are ſo near.</hi> And we well know how altogether Popiſh we are in our Ceremonies, according to their opinion. And we being as near their Diſcipline, as they are to our Ceremonies, and Government, may we not as well ſay, Indeed it were more ſafe for us to conform our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Ceremonies to the Heathens, than to the Diſciplinarians, which are ſo near? And thus ye ſee, how according to their principles we are like to come to a good agreement, and an happy compoſure, as when they would ſmooth over the matter they diſſemblingly ſpeak, calling ſmall and new Acquifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions, Moderation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, They ſay, that Indifferent things ought to remain ſo, and they ought not to be obliged any further than Chriſt and the Scripture binds them.</p>
               <p>The firſt part of this argument is as falſe, dangerous and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to all Churches and all Eccleſiaſtical Authority, as the wit of man can invent any thing; and is quite contrary to Scriptures, which require obedience (as likewiſe themſelves do being in power) to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors. And therefore to deny Superiors that wherein only their power is ſeen and exerciſed, is to take away what the Scripture grants them. Now to the ſecond part. Chriſt and the Scripture oblige men to be ſubject in ſuch caſes to men:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvinus</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus <hi>Anaba.</hi> pag. 27.2. in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tavo.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Calvin</hi> expreſsly ſaith, <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probare quod nunquam improbavit Deus, nimiae eſt hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni inquam mortali temeritatis &amp; arrogantia: Hoe autem perpetuò teneamus,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104650:39"/>uſurpari,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                  <q>To condemn that which God never Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, is too great raſhneſs and arrogance for Mortal man. But let us hold to this conſtantly, that the autority of God is uſurped, when that which he hath permitted is condemned.</q> And ſhow where God hath not permitted any one of our Rites, or Ceremonies. And if ye cannor (as we are ſure you cannot;) How do ye not take Gods Office out of his hands in condemning that he hath not, being all Private men, and of no authority over us? To this, let us add Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> ſpeaking thus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkins</hi> on <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. v. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Things are not called Indifferent, becauſe we may uſe them indifferently, or not uſe them, when we will, and how we will: but becauſe in themſelves, or in their own nature they are neither good, nor evil; and we may again not uſe them well, or ill: Furthermore, there are two things which Reſtrain the uſe of things Indifferent, The Law of Charity, and the Laws of Men, &amp;c.</hi> ANd the ſame Author in another place ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkins</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Actions Indifferent in the caſe of Offence, or Edification, ceaſe to be Indifferent, and come under ſome Commandment of the Moral Law.</hi> In which, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If eating Fleſh will Offend.</hi> &amp;c. Thus he. Now eating Fleſh doth offend at ſome times, and that not equals, of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, but Superiours; And a man would think, that a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Conſcience ought to have greater regard to theſe, than to other perſons.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> And yet we find true what <hi>Calvin</hi> laught at in his daies thus, <q>You may ſee ſome, who imagine their Liberty cannot hold, unleſs by eating Fleſh on <hi>Fridays,</hi> they ſtand poſſeſſed of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, becauſe they ſee their own acts to teſtifie ſo expreſly againſt Toleration, in raiſing and acting one of the moſt ſad and unjuſt Tragedies that ever <hi>England</hi> felt, and groaned under; and this principally to introduce a ſtrange Worſhip, contrary to the Laws, and Conſciences of ſo many Thouſands, and their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, it not being poſſible to ſhake this off them, ſome of them ſhift thus, away: That if they did evil, we ought not to do ſo too. For though the matter be ſo groſs, that for arguments ſake they do ſeem outwardly to relent, and recede from their injuſtice, and rigour, to the end, they may with more confidence demand favour at our hands, to whom they could do no juſtice; yet in truth they repent of nothing ſo much, as that they did not uſe greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities towards us, appears by their reſerving to themſelves, all true ſigns and effects of true Repentance: For to one another or to the People, whom they have groſly miſſed ſo far, that it is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104650:40"/>frequent with them to ſay, that they could conform, but that they have taught the People otherwiſe, (an imprudent, as well as an ungodly evaſion) they never make any ſuch acknowledgement: But whereas they, upon the nature of true Repentance, are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do their plain and utmoſt indeavours to undeceive, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them to the truth; they on the contrary, uſe all ſubtile and ſecret artifices to nouriſh ſuch wicked Errours as they have bred in them, while they themſelves in cloſe diſcourſe being expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated with,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corbet's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</note> for the occaſion, will ſay as Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> doth, There might be ſome exceſs heretofore, by the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> committed. But to the Point: It no ways followeth, that if the <hi>Presbyte ians</hi> offended (and that notoriouſly) in Perſecuting deadly the Church, therefore a retaliation of the ſame meaſure ſhould be called (as they would have it) revenge, or be unjuſt. For, waving at preſent the differences of the Cauſes (which how ever equal and indifferent judges would certainly give againſt them) they no doubt will to the laſt keep up diſputable) the manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and acting make a foul difference. For there was wanting all Legal Authority both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, on that ſide; and yet dreaded they not to impoſe their pleaſures and Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both, on their bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hren; who were no more ſuject to them, than were they to theſe; but alſo uſurped over their Governours too, and brought them either to obey their Wills, or ſuffer their Vengeance: Which was an higher piece of iniquitie than that of the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf. For as we of this Church were free from his power; ſo have we nothing to do to give law to him: But theſe men were in all Lawful and Canonical ſubjection under thoſe they would give Law unto, as well in Reference to Conſcience, as Civil propertie. Yet am I not without a Witneſs of their own againſt them, even in this Particular. For thus reaſonably writes one of them.
<note place="margin">Myſteries of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abbala. <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <q>We declare it, that it is true indeed we cannot come up in all things to their judgment who are over us, as we know they could not come up to ours, when we were advanced over them. As we could not allow them any publick imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or encouragement, when they could not comply with us, and our Laws and Conſtitutions. So we cannot expect any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick imployment, or incouragement from them, now we Diſſent from them,</q> and cannot cloſe with their Laws and Conſtitutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This hath much of Ingenuity, if we compare it with the more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104650:40"/>common temper of them, which leads them only to take away Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from others, but to grant none. But neither muſt we ſuffer this conceſſion to paſs without Cenſure. For according to their common and current Craft with the Ignorant, fain they would ſhuffle and confound all Power ſo and Lawful Authority, as that theirs it ſhould fairly and fully be, who can lay hold of it by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and retain it by Violence: And therefore becauſe once indeed by ſpoil and rapine, they poſſeſſed themſelves of Power in Church and State; do they compare themſelves with ſuch, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom it deſcends fairly and orderly, by the received courſe of known Juſtice and Religion. But grant them this, we grant them almoſt all: But they muſt know, there is an infinite diſparity, which they can never remove, though they have put fair for it, ſome of them in reſolving, Firſt, all Civil-Power, and next, with little more infatuation and boldneſs, all Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the power of the People; and the power of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, into the power of the Sword. So that Perſon, or thoſe ſhould be unqueſtionably veſted in Civil Dominion, and that Society rightly conſtituted in Eccleſiaſtical Rule, who have inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſame, and are able to hold it: A Tenet of which I ſhall ſpeak no more at preſent than I have already, only that God would give us if not Grace, human Prudence, and reaſon ſo far to judg of, as may draw us to lament and prevent by humble Suits the unavoidable Diſaſters and Confuſions it muſt again cover the face of that Earth with where it abides; And that God would reſtore ſo much of loſt man in us, before we pretend to be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (and that of the beſt ſort) as to ſtand to our own Judgments and not to alter and vary according to our advantage, and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our eſpouſed Intereſts; producing quarrels and babbles to Eternity it ſelf, if we could live ſo long; as they certainly would, who will neither yield to Reaſon, nor ſuffer their own Rules and Opinions to take place in them, ſo as to reduce them to order.</p>
               <p>But the ſolemn and indiſſoluble band of their League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt caſt upon themſelves and others in authority, muſt by no means be violated; and beſides, ſome Poſteriorities are pretended &amp; urged to the great advantage of the Diſcipline, and theſe ariſing from promiſes made of having regard to tender Conſciences upon the entrance of his Majeſty into his Throne, and ſome Diſciplinarians great merits.</p>
               <p>To the firſt part of theſe, it may be reaſonably demanded, What
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104650:41"/>that ſtrange ſacredneſs is, what unheard-of Excellency it hath, and new divineneſs that neither any Oaths or Obligations, wherewith men were bound before, nor any which they have ſince regularly taken, ſhould be of any force or vertue at all againſt the Covenant? But what ever went before, is made void by the Covenant, what ever follows is made abortive by the Covenant. How comes this about? Was the authority of the Inventers, or the juſt power of the propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or the divineneſs and ſacredneſs of the matter ſuch that this, and none but this, muſt be of any validity or worth with us? Nothing leſs ſure: For, all theſe are unanſw. Arg. againſt it; for, neither circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<note place="margin">The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants Plea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</note> nor ſubſtance was either legal, or juſt, or holy; as may appear from the infinite falſifications, direct falſities both as to Hiſtory and Reaſon, with which that Treatiſe is fraught to juſtifieit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm men of little conſcience and judgment, in that bond of Iniquity.</p>
               <p>But let their great Caſuiſt <hi>Alexander Hirderſon</hi> be here admitted to ſpeak, and how eaſie will it be to reſolve this doubt? That King of Bleſſed Memory to whom he wrote, to his own confuſion; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting againſt his New Oath the Covenant, his old Oaths taken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the contrary at his Coronation, was then anſwered that the Parliament and people to whom they were made, might free him from ſuch engagements, (not that the King ever made ſuch Oaths otherwiſe to Parliaments in his ſenſe, but as they are the Peoples Repreſentatives.) Which though as the King ſolidly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, is a falſe Suppoſition, yet hereby are evident the principles of ſuch Doctors, that Parliaments may lawfully quit the Prince of Oaths taken in reference to the People. Therefore, according to them, the perfect Parliament having not only declared againſt ſuch Obligations, but by ſtrong reaſons manifeſted the nullity of them; what pretence can they have who are, and always were, but private men in ſuch caſes to urge their <hi>Soveraign</hi> with ſuch burdens &amp; bonds?</p>
               <p>But further, The pretended promiſe was made to tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and how doth it appear that the Presbyterians are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under that expreſſion? We abſolutely deny the ſame. And what force can their bare Aſſertions and Teſtimonies given of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be to prove it; when we have ſuch ſtore of Inſtances of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact which no men of good Conſcience, much leſs tender in the received ſenſe, can willingly commit, and much leſs perſevere to juſtifie? But if it muſt be ſo, that ſuch a ſenſe of tenderneſs of Conſcience muſt needs be true becauſe 'tis common and current, How will they not in opening that door for themſelves let in ſuch a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104650:41"/>Rabble as they ſhall have but little joy in their poſſeſſions? Will they multiply beggarly proofs, and ſay, They are a ſober, a godly, a moderate party; and ſo conclude juſt as much as they did before?</p>
               <p>To ſhut up all, ſome there are who diſtinguiſh of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. For, they are (ſay they) either peaceable, or unquiet and ſeditious: The ſeditious and unquiet Heretick or Schiſmatick (according to theſe) may not be ſuffered, but the modeſt, and ſober,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mentzerus</hi> in <hi>Exegeſi Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanae Confeſſ. Art.</hi> 10.</note> and peaceable ought to be born with; and this is <hi>Mentzerus</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and the Plea of both Papiſt and Puritan with us at preſent. For now forſooth, <hi>No ſuch good Subjects as Catholicks.</hi> And the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> himſelf writes at large, <hi>Saints no Smiters.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thomb</hi>'s Saints no Smiters.</note> And now go round about, enter into the midſt of all that have been bitter Enemies to the King, and you muſt have as rare luck as he that draws a Prize at a Lottery, if you can pick out a diſloyal ſubject; in diſcourſe, All Factions contend which ſhould pretend moſt Loyalty.</p>
               <p>But in anſwer to this diſtinction, we ſhall craveleave in like manner to diſtinguiſh of Rooks: for, ſome Rooks ſet upon trees, and they pick not up the new-ſown Corn, and therefore may be born with, and not moleſted; and ſome Rooks ſet upon Lands, and they are not to be ſuffered, for they do hurt to Corn. Juſt ſuch an one, and ſo to be favoured is the Heretick and Schiſmatick. I confeſs, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction had been tolerable, had it been made of the Abſtracts, <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Hereſies.</hi> For true it may be, that ſome of both ſorts contain nothing in them turbulent or ſeditious. But to take this in the Concrete, Schiſmaticks and Hereticks, is no leſs ridiculous than we have made; and no leſs falſly ſuppoſed of them who at preſent put it into their Pleas than of any other. Are not they, think we, of a very gentle quiet, and peaceable Nature and Diſpoſition who being in power (not elſe you may be ſure) in purſuance of their Schiſm, turned out of their Livings but 85 Miniſters of the 97 Pariſhes within the Walls of <hi>London,</hi> whereof 16. died with ſorrow, and 14 out of the 16. Pariſhes, without the Walls, and out of the 10. Out-Pariſhes 9; and ſo proportionably where they were Maſters;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. Natur. Hist. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 37.</note> eſpecially while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the very ſame Principles, whereby they ſo acted: <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us that the Lion as fierce a beaſt as it is, may be made very gentle and tame by ſevere and ſeaſonable treatments, ſo that one may ſuffer it to lick his very fleſh; but his tongue being very rough, if in fawning and licking he chances to draw the leaſt blood from a man, together with its ſlaver, he is ſo raviſht with the ſavorineſs of it, that he is put into rage &amp; fury. So in truth, no queſtion but the fierceſt <hi>Sciſmatick</hi> or <hi>Heretick</hi> may be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104650:42"/>brought to a very gentle and familiar condition; but ſuffer him to have ſuch neer acceſs to Majeſty, as to but taſte the infinite ſweets of Power, and Rule; through a ſecure confidence in his general Innocency, ſo tranſported is he beyond his own ordinary, yet unnatural and forced tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that his Ingenuity will ſoon end in injuſtice, and his fairneſs in fury: And then ſhall you beg Toleration of him, and be ſure to go without it and that deſervedly.</p>
               <p>Some there are of no mean place and policie, who adviſe ſeriouſly, to avoid the Infamy of Perſecuting poor Souls for Religion, and let them be Executioners of their own Miſchief and Ruine: For (ſay they) Let them (for inſtance the <hi>Quakers</hi>) alone, and in time they will certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one another. Which I may eaſily grant to be true, and yet the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel very weak, and unreaſonable. For 'tis true, that many Religions ſhall I call them or superſtitions rather, now pleading for Toleration, would in their progreſs fall foul with themſelves, and they devoted to them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found one another. And it is moſt probable, if Wild-Beaſts were ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from their Pens into ſome open place they would tear and worrey one another to Piece, but not till they had put to flight, or devoured their Keepers. It is very likely, that <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> of the ſame Denomination, would in time Fight out the truth of Religion amongſt them; but their Common Enemy (as they call us) muſt firſt lye gaſping at their Feet. And will it not be a notable Solace to a wiſe man to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, that by caſting away his own life for nothing, preparation will be made to deſtroy his Adverſary? ſuch is the ſafety in many Religions.</p>
               <p>The Decencie (to all ſober Chriſtians) is anſwerable to the ſafety. For, as <hi>Lucian</hi> tells how <hi>Ptolemie</hi> Son of <hi>Lagus</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ented to his People a Black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amel for a Show, a thing, where thoſe Beaſts abound moſt, never ſeen; and a Man one half of whom was perfect Black, and the other half of his Body very Fair. It the Camel they all ſtood amazed: but at the Man, moſt of the beholders burſt out into a loud laughter; others in ſcorn and deteſtation turned away from ſuch a ridiculous Monſter, and reproach to mankind: and yet this perſon differed not from other men, as to parts, or ſubſtance, but Ceremonie only, and Accidents: So what ever may be Tolerated, and perhaps Admired in matters not of divine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and nature in Religion to exhibit a Church to Chriſtian ſpectators ſo moſt ſtrangly divided and diſſonant to it ſelf, though but in things, not Eſſential or Subſtantial to Faith, but circumſtances, is to render it ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to one half of the World, the merry ſort; and to the other ſort, the ſober and judicious, odious, and ſo Scandalous, that few of theſe will ever yield to become <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to it, or tarry with it long. And we may be ſure, that they whoſe Policy, rather than Piety, or Prudence incline them to favour ſuch Monſtroſities, have nothing ſo much in their deſign as to have us laughed out of the preſent Religion, and to make way for No Religion or for another Religion. For to encounter either of which nothing can be more profitable than by a generous Conſtancy, to follow and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in our own Religion: For then will the ſlie underminer of it, find himſelf in the end bafled, the impudent oppoſer aſhamed, and the witty ſcoffer, ridiculous to himſelf, having nothing elſe to bear him out but bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and multitude of Offenders.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
